<?xml-model href="../digmethodsfem_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<document>
    <meta>
        <title>LETTERS ON THE EQUALITY OF THE SEXES, AND THE CONDITION OF WOMAN.</title>
        <author>SARAH GRIMKE</author> ADDRESSED TO MARY S. PARKER, PRESIDENT OF THE Boston Female
        Anti-Slavery Society. BOSTON: <source>PUBLISHED BY ISAAC KNAPP, 25, CORNHILL.</source>
        <publication_date>1838</publication_date>. </meta>

    <main>
        <structure header="main"> LETTERS.</structure>
        <structure le="1">
            <structure p="head"><structure header="1"> LETTER I. </structure>
            </structure><structure subhead="1">THE ORIGINAL EQUALITY OF WOMAN. </structure>
            <structure date="July 11th, 1837">
                <setting>Amesbury</setting>, 7th Mo. 11th, 1837. </structure>
            <!-- le wraps each full header
header formatting applies to the heading of each letter eg "LETTER X"
subhead formatting applies to subheading of each letter eg "THE ORIGINAL EQUALITY OF WOMAN"
-->> <structure p="1"> My Dear Friend,— In attempting to comply with thy request to give
                my views on the Province of Woman, I feel that I am venturing on nearly untrodden
                ground, and that <religion r_quaker="anti-anglican">I shall advance arguments in
                    opposition to a corrupt public opinion, and to the perverted interpretation of
                    Holy Writ</religion>, which has so universally obtained. But I am in search of
                truth; and no obstacle shall prevent my prosecuting that search, because I believe
                the welfare of the world will be materially advanced by every new discovery we make
                of the <religion r_christianity="determinism">designs of Jehovah in the creation of
                    woman</religion>. It is impossible that we can answer the purpose of our being,
                unless we understand that purpose. It is impossible that we should fulfil our
                duties, unless we comprehend them; or live up to our privileges, unless we know what
                they are. </structure>
            <structure p="2"> In examining this important subject, <religion
                    r_quaker="Grimke's religion">I shall depend solely on the Bible to designate the
                    sphere of woman</religion>, because I believe almost every thing that has been
                written on this subject, has been the result of a misconception of the simple truths
                revealed in the Scriptures, in consequence of the false translation of many passages
                of Holy Writ. <religion r_anglican="On the Church of England and KJB"> My mind is
                    entirely delivered from the superstitious reverence which is attached to the
                    English version of the Bible. King James’s translators certainly were not
                    inspired.</religion> I therefore claim the original as my standard, believing
                that to have been inspired, and I also claim to judge for myself what is the meaning
                of the inspired writers, because <s_theory
                    s_enlightenment_individualism="Potentially Protestant "> I believe it to be the
                    solemn duty of every individual to search the Scriptures for themselves, with
                    the aid of the Holy Spirit, and not be governed by the views of any man, or set
                    of men.</s_theory>
            </structure>
            <structure p="3">
                <religion r_christianity="general">We must first view woman at the period of her
                    creation.</religion> ‘And God said, Let us make man in our own image, after our
                likeness; and let them have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the fowl of
                the air, and over the cattle, and over all the earth, and over every creeping thing
                that creepeth upon the earth. So God created man in his own image, in the image of
                God created he him, male and female created he them.’ <s_theory
                    s_rights_of_man="Natural Rights"> In all this sublime description of the
                    creation of man, (which is a generic term including man and woman,) there is not
                    one particle of difference intimated as existing between them. They were both
                    made in the image of God; dominion was given to both over every other creature,
                    but not over each other. Created in perfect equality, they were expected to
                    exercise the vicegerence intrusted to them by their Maker, in harmony and love.
                </s_theory>
            </structure>
            <structure p="4">
                <religion r_christianity="general">Let us pass on now to the recapitulation of the
                    creation of man:</religion>—‘<structure q="bible">The Lord God formed man of the
                    dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and man
                    became a living soul. And the Lord God said, it is not good that man should be
                    alone, I will make him an help meet for him.’</structure>
                <s_theory s_natural_rights="Evolutionary creationism ">All creation swarmed with
                    animated beings capable of natural affection, as we know they still are; it was
                    not, therefore, merely to give man a creature susceptible of loving, obeying,
                    and looking up to him, for all that the animals could do and did do. It was to
                    give him a companion, in all respects his equal; one who was like himself a free
                    agent, gifted with intellect and endowed with immortality; not a partaker merely
                    of his animal gratifications, but able to enter into all his feelings as a moral
                    and responsible being.</s_theory> If this had not been the case, how could she
                have been an help meet for him? <s_theory
                    s_natural_rights="determinism, theistic view of natural rights">I understand
                    this as applying not only to the parties entering into the marriage contract,
                    but to all men and women, because I believe God designed woman to be an help
                    meet for man in every good and perfect work</s_theory>. She was a part of
                himself, as if Jehovah designed to make the oneness and identity of man and woman
                perfect and complete; and when the glorious work of their creation was finished,
                ‘the morning stars sang together, and all the sons of God shouted for joy.’ </structure>
            <structure p="5">
                <religion r_christianity="Eve, apple">This blissful condition was not long enjoyed
                    by our first parents. Eve, it would seem from the history, was wandering alone
                    amid the bowers of Paradise, when the serpent met with her.</religion>
                <religion r_christianity="Eve">From her reply to Satan, it is evident that the
                    command not to eat ‘of the tree that is in the midst of the garden,’ was given
                    to both, although the term man was used when the prohibition was issued by
                    God.</religion> ‘And the woman said unto the serpent, WE may eat of the fruit of
                the trees of the garden, but of the fruit of the tree which is in the midst of the
                garden, <religion r_christianity="Eve's ignorance">God hath said, YE shall not eat
                    of it, neither shall YE touch it, lest YE die.’ Here the woman was exposed to
                    temptation from a being with whom she was unacquainted. She had been accustomed
                    to associate with her beloved partner, and to hold communion with God and with
                    angels; but of satanic intelligence, she was in all probability entirely
                    ignorant. Through the subtlety of the serpent, she was beguiled.</religion> And
                ‘when she saw that the tree was good for food, and that it was pleasant to the eyes,
                and a tree to be desired to make one wise, she took of the fruit thereof and did
                eat.’ </structure>
            <structure p="6">
                <power_system
                    p_religion="socio-religious, adam + eve equally susceptible to influence but retain state of no sin through piety"
                    >We next find Adam involved in the same sin, not through the instrumentality of
                    a supernatural agent, but through that of his equal, a being whom he must have
                    known was liable to transgress the divine command, because he must have felt
                    that he was himself a free agent, and that he was restrained from disobedience
                    only by the exercise of faith and love towards his Creator.</power_system>
                <s_theory s_natural_rights="Religious justification; Adam not superior to Eve">Had
                    Adam tenderly reproved his wife, and endeavored to lead her to repentance
                    instead of sharing in her guilt, I should be much more ready to accord to man
                    that superiority which he claims; but as the facts stand disclosed by the sacred
                    historian, it appears to me that to say the least, there was as much weakness
                    exhibited by Adam as by Eve. They both fell from innocence, and consequently
                    from happiness, but not from equality. </s_theory>
            </structure>
            <structure p="7"> Let us next examine the conduct of this fallen pair, when Jehovah
                interrogated them respecting their fault. They both frankly confessed their guilt.
                    <structure q="Uncredited, likely Biblical">‘The man said, the woman whom thou
                    gavest to be with me, she gave me of the tree and I did eat. And the woman said,
                    the serpent beguiled me and I did eat.’ <power_system
                        p_patriarchy="God ordained Adam to rule over Eve">And the Lord God said unto
                        the woman, ‘Thou wilt be subject unto thy husband, and he will rule over
                        thee.’</power_system></structure>
                <power_system p_social="Disagreeing with patrriarchical interpretation">That this
                    did not allude to the subjection of woman to man is manifest, because the same
                    mode of expression is used in speaking to Cain of Abel.</power_system> The truth
                is that the curse, as it is termed, which was pronounced by Jehovah upon woman, is a
                simple prophecy. The Hebrew, like the French language, uses the same word to express
                shall and will. Our translators having been accustomed to exercise lordship over
                their wives, and seeing only through the medium of a perverted judgment, very
                naturally, though I think not very learnedly or very kindly, translated it shall
                instead of will, and thus converted a prediction to Eve into a command to Adam; for
                observe, it is addressed to the woman and not to the man. The consequence of the
                fall was an immediate struggle for dominion, and Jehovah foretold which would gain
                the ascendency; <religion
                    r_quaker="Genesis 9:6, interpreted as sin makes no value distinction between people"
                    >but as he created them in his image, as that image manifestly was not lost by
                    the fall, because it is urged in Gen. 9: 6, as an argument why the life of man
                    should not be taken by his fellow man, there is no reason to suppose that sin
                    produced any distinction between them as moral, intellectual and responsible
                    beings.</religion> Man might just as well have endeavored by hard labor to
                fulfil the prophecy, thorns and thistles will the earth bring forth to thee, as to
                pretend to accomplish the other, ‘he will rule over thee,’ by asserting dominion
                over his wife. </structure>
            <structure p="8">
                <structure po="1">
                    <structure l="1">‘Authority usurped from God, not given.</structure>
                    <structure l="2">He gave him only over beast, flesh, fowl, </structure>
                    <structure l="3">Dominion absolute: that right he holds</structure>
                    <structure l="4">By God’s donation: but man o’er woman</structure>
                    <structure l="5">He made not Lord, such title to himself </structure>
                    <structure l="6">Reserving, human left from human free.</structure>’
                </structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="9">
                <power_system p_religion="Women not subject to patriarchy but to Christian God">Here
                    then I plant myself. God created us equal;—he created us free agents;—he is our
                    Lawgiver, our King and our Judge, and to him alone is woman bound to be in
                    subjection, and to him alone is she accountable for the use of those talents
                    with which her Heavenly Father has entrusted her.</power_system> One is her
                Master even Christ. </structure>
            <structure p="sig1">Thine for the oppressed in the bonds of womanhood,</structure>
            <structure sig="Grimke"> Sarah M. Grimke </structure>. </structure>
        <!-- End letter 1-->
        <structure le="2">
            <structure header="2">LETTER II. </structure>
            <structure subhead="2">WOMAN SUBJECT ONLY TO GOD. </structure>
            <structure date="July 17th, 1837"><setting>Newburyport</setting>, 7th mo. 17, 1837. </structure>
            <structure p="10"> My dear Sister,—In my last, I traced the creation and the fall of man
                and woman from that state of purity and happiness which their beneficent Creator
                designed them to enjoy. As they were one in transgression, their chastisement was
                the same. <structure q="Uncredited, likely Biblical">‘So God drove out the man, and
                    he placed at the East of the garden of Eden a cherubim and a flaming sword,
                    which turned every way to keep the way of the tree of life.’</structure> We now
                behold them expelled from Paradise, fallen from their original loveliness, but still
                bearing on their foreheads the image and superscription of Jehovah; still invested
                with high moral responsibilities, intellectual powers, and immortal souls. <s_theory
                    s_natural_rights="Religious justification">They had incurred the penalty of sin,
                    they were shorn of their innocence, but they stood on the same platform side by
                    side, acknowledging no superior but their God.</s_theory>
                <power_system p_patriarchy="Woman introduced sin">Notwithstanding what has been
                    urged, woman I am aware stands charged to the present day with having brought
                    sin into the world.</power_system> I shall not repel the charge by any counter
                assertions, although, as was before hinted, Adam’s ready acquiescence with his
                wife’s proposal, does not savor much of that superiority in strength of mind, which
                is arrogated by man. <power_system
                    p_patriarchy="Men have benefit or are satisfied with undervaluing women">Even
                    admitting that Eve was the greater sinner, it seems to me man might be satisfied
                    with the dominion he has claimed and exercised for nearly six thousand years,
                    and that more true nobility would be manifested by endeavoring to raise the
                    fallen and invigorate the weak, than by keeping woman in
                    subjection.</power_system> But I ask no favors for my sex. I surrender not our
                claim to equality. <power_system
                    p_patriarchy="If women are not freed from patriarchical rule, they will become weaker"
                    > All I ask of our brethren is, that they will take their feet from off our
                    necks, and permit us to stand upright on that ground which God designed us to
                    occupy. If he has not given us the rights which have, as I conceive, been
                    wrested from us, we shall soon give evidence of our inferiority, and shrink back
                    into that obscurity, which the high souled magnanimity of man has assigned us as
                    our appropriate sphere.</power_system></structure>
            <structure p="11">As I am unable to learn from sacred writ when woman was deprived by
                God of her equality with man, I shall touch upon a few points in the Scriptures,
                which demonstrate that no supremacy was granted to man. When God had destroyed the
                world, except Noah and his family, by the deluge, he renewed the grant formerly made
                to man, and again gave him dominion over every beast of the earth, every fowl of the
                air, over all that moveth upon the earth, and over all the fishes of the sea; into
                his hands they were delivered. <s_theory s_natural_rights="Religious justificatoin"
                    >But was woman, bearing the image of her God, placed under the dominion of her
                    fellow man? Never! Jehovah could not surrender his authority to govern his own
                    immortal creatures into the hands of a being, whom he knew, and whom his whole
                    history proved, to be unworthy of a trust so sacred and important. God could not
                    do it, because it is a direct contravention of his law, </s_theory>
                <structure q="Uncredited, likely Biblical">‘Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and
                    him only shalt thou serve.’</structure><religion r_christianity="General">
                    <s_theory s_natural_rights="Religious justification">If Jehovah had appointed
                        man as the guardian, or teacher of woman, he would certainly have given some
                        intimation of this surrender of his own prerogative. But so far from it, we
                        find the commands of God invariably the same to man and woman; and not the
                        slightest intimation is given in a single passage of the Bible, that God
                        designed to point woman to man as her instructor.</s_theory></religion> The
                tenor of his language always is, ‘Look unto ME, and be ye saved, all the ends of the
                earth, for I am God, and there is none else.’ </structure>
            <structure p="12"><religion
                    r_christianity="Corruption and sin equally represented between sexes">The lust
                    of dominion was probably the first effect of the fall; and as there was no other
                    intelligent being over whom to exercise it, woman was the first victim of this
                    unhallowed passion. We afterwards see it exhibited by Cain in the murder of his
                    brother, by Nimrod in his becoming a mighty hunter of men, and setting up a
                    kingdom over which to reign. Here we see the origin of that Upas of slavery,
                    which sprang up immediately after the fall, and has spread its pestilential
                    branches over the whole face of the known world.</religion>
                <power_system p_patriarchy="Historical">All history attests that man has subjected
                    woman to his will, used her as a means to promote his selfish gratification, to
                    minister to his sensual pleasures, to be instrumental in promoting his comfort;
                    but never has he desired to elevate her to that rank she was created to fill. He
                    has done all he could to debase and enslave her mind; and now he looks
                    triumphantly on the ruin he has wrought, and says, the being he has thus deeply
                    injured is his inferior.</power_system></structure>
            <structure p="13"><power_system
                    p_patriarchy="Women oppressed in 'all ages and countries'">Woman has been placed
                    by John Quincy Adams, side by side with the slave, whilst he was contending for
                    the right side of petition. I thank him for ranking us with the oppressed; for I
                    shall not find it difficult to show, that in all ages and countries, not even
                    excepting enlightened republican America, woman has more or less been made a
                    means to promote the welfare of man, without due regard to her own happiness,
                    and the glory of God as the end of her creation.</power_system>
            </structure>
            <structure p="14"><power_system p_patriarchy="Defines patriarchy as former period"
                    >During the patriarchal ages, we find men and women engaged in the same
                    employments.</power_system> Abraham and Sarah both assisted in preparing the
                food which was to be set before the three men, who visited them in the plains of
                Mamre; but although their occupations were similar, <power_system
                    p_patriarchy="Male family excerts control over female family">Sarah was not
                    permitted to enjoy the society of the holy visitant; and as we learn from Peter,
                    that she ‘obeyed Abraham, calling him Lord,’ we may presume he exercised
                    dominion over her.</power_system> We shall pass on now to Rebecca. In her
                history, we find another striking illustration of the low estimation in which woman
                was held. Eleazur is sent to seek a wife for Isaac. He finds Rebecca going down to
                the well to fill her pitcher. He accosts her; and she replies with all humility,
                ‘Drink, my lord.’ How does he endeavor to gain her favor and confidence? Does he
                approach her as a dignified creature, whom he was about to invite to fill an
                important station in his master’s family, as the wife of his only son? No. He
                offered incense to her vanity, and ‘he took a golden ear-ring of half a shekel
                weight, and two bracelets for her hands of ten shekels weight of gold,’ and gave
                them to Rebecca.</structure>
            <structure p="15"><religion r_christianity="Cupidity, sin of greed">The cupidity of man
                    soon led him to regard woman as property, and hence we find them sold to those,
                    who wished to marry them, as far as appears, without any regard to those sacred
                    rights which belong to woman, as well as to man in the choice of a
                    companion.</religion> That women were a profitable kind of property, we may
                gather from the description of a virtuous woman in the last chapter of Proverbs. To
                work willingly with her hands, to open her hands to the poor, to clothe herself with
                silk and purple, to look well to her household, to make fine linen and sell it, to
                deliver girdles to the merchant, and not to eat the bread of idleness, seems to have
                constituted in the view of Solomon, the perfection of a woman’s character and
                achievements. <structure
                    q="Abolitionist and women's rights activist Lydia Maria Child's 'Condition of Women, in Various Ages and Nations', 1835"
                    >‘The spirit of that age was not favorable to intellectual improvement; but
                        <s_theory
                        s_enlightenment_individualism=" Individual intelligent people create societal progress, regardless of gender"
                        >as there were wise men who formed exceptions to the general ignorance, and
                        were destined to guide the world into more advanced states, so there was a
                        corresponding proportion of wise women</s_theory>; <religion
                        r_judaism="Unlike English/American Christianity, Judaism views women as holier than men"
                        >and among the Jews, as well as other nations, we find a strong tendency to
                        believe that women were in more immediate connection with heaven than
                        men.</religion>’</structure>—L. M. Child’s Con. of Woman. If there be any
                truth in this tradition, I am at a loss to imagine in what the superiority of man
                consists.</structure>
            <structure p="sig2">Thine in the bonds of womanhood,</structure>
            <structure sig="Grimke"> Sarah M. Grimke </structure>. </structure>
        <!--End letter 2 -->
        <structure le="4">
            <!--End letter 3 -->
            <structure header="4">LETTER IV.</structure>
            <structure subhead="4">SOCIAL INTERCOURSE OF THE SEXES. </structure>
            <structure date="July 27th, 1837"><setting>Andover</setting>, 7th Mo. 27th, 1837. </structure>
            <structure p="25">My Dear Friend,—Before I proceed with the account of that oppression
                which woman has suffered in every age and country from her protector, man, permit me
                to offer for your consideration, some views relative to the social intercourse of
                the sexes. Nearly the whole of this intercourse is, in my apprehension, derogatory
                to man and woman, as moral and intellectual beings. We approach each other, and
                mingle with each other, under the constant pressure of a feeling that we are of
                different sexes; and, instead of regarding each other only in the light of immortal
                creatures, the mind is fettered by the idea which is early and industriously infused
                into it, <f_theory f_terf="gender essentialism">that we must never forget the
                    distinction between male and female</f_theory>. Hence our intercourse, instead
                of being elevated and refined, is generally calculated to excite and keep alive the
                lowest propensities of our nature. Nothing, I believe, has tended more to destroy
                the true dignity of woman, than the fact that she is approached by man in the
                character of a female. The idea that she is sought as an intelligent and heaven-born
                creature, whose society will cheer, refine and elevate her companion, and that she
                will receive the same blessings she confers, is rarely held up to her view.
                    <power_system
                    p_patriarchy="Men view women as weaker, take advantage based on this">On the
                    contrary, man almost always addresses himself to the weakness of woman. By
                    flattery, by an appeal to her passions, he seeks access to her heart; and when
                    he has gained her affections, he uses her as the instrument of his pleasure—the
                    minister of his temporal comfort. He furnishes himself with a housekeeper, whose
                    chief business is in the kitchen, or the nursery. And whilst he goes abroad and
                    enjoys the means of improvement afforded by collision of intellect with
                    cultivated minds, his wife is condemned to draw nearly all her instruction from
                    books, if she has time to peruse them; and if not, from her meditations, whilst
                    engaged in those domestic duties, which are necessary for the comfort of her
                    lord and master.</power_system>
            </structure>
            <structure p="26"><religion
                    r_christianity="Christians should believe that womens' potential is subdued by patriarchy"
                    >Surely no one who contemplates, with the eye of a Christian philosopher, the
                    design of God in the creation of woman, can believe that she is now fulfilling
                    that design.</religion> The literal translation of the word ‘help-meet’ is a
                helper like unto himself; it is so rendered in the <religion
                    r_christianity="Greek old testament">Septuagint</religion>, and manifestly
                signifies a companion. <power_system
                    p_patriarchy="Men + patriarchy hold women back from natural potential">Now I
                    believe it will be impossible for woman to fill the station assigned her by God,
                    until her brethren mingle with her as an equal, as a moral being; and lose, in
                    the dignity of her immortal nature, and in the fact of her bearing like himself
                    the image and superscription of her God, the idea of her being a
                    female.</power_system> The apostle beautifully remarks, <structure q="Apostle"
                    >‘As many of you as have been baptized into Christ, have put on Christ. There is
                    neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither bond nor free, there is neither male nor
                    female; for ye are all one in Christ Jesus.’</structure>
                <f_theory
                    f_enlightenment_individualism="Women should be viewed as autonomous individuals"
                    >Until our intercourse is purified by the forgetfulness of sex,—until we rise
                    above the present low and sordid views which entwine themselves around our
                    social and domestic interchange of sentiment and feelings, we never can derive
                    that benefit from each other’s society which it is the design of our Creator
                    that we should.</f_theory>
                <power_system p_patriarchy="Society run by men is upheld by both sexes">Man has
                    inflicted an unspeakable injury upon woman, by holding up to her view her animal
                    nature, and placing in the back ground her moral and intellectual being. Woman
                    has inflicted an injury upon herself by submitting to be thus regarded; and she
                    is now called upon to rise from the station where man, not God, has placed her,
                    and claim those sacred and inalienable rights, as a moral and responsible being,
                    with which her Creator has invested her. </power_system></structure>
            <structure p="27">What but these views, so derogatory to the character of woman, could
                have called forth the remark contained in the Pastoral Letter? ‘We especially
                deplore the intimate acquaintance and promiscuous conversation of females with
                regard to things “which ought not to be named,” by which that modesty and delicacy,
                which is the charm of domestic life, and which constitutes the true influence of
                woman, is consumed.’<power_system
                    p_social="Men wish to prevent women from speaking about 'immodest' subjects">
                    How wonderful that the conceptions of man relative to woman are so low, that he
                    cannot perceive that she may converse on any subject connected with the
                    improvement of her species, without swerving in the least from that modesty
                    which is one of her greatest virtues!</power_system> Is it designed to insinuate
                that woman should possess a greater degree of modesty than man? This idea I utterly
                reprobate. Or is it supposed that woman cannot go into scenes of misery, the
                necessary result of those very things, which the Pastoral Letter says ought not to
                be named, for the purpose of moral reform, without becoming contaminated by those
                with whom she thus mingles? </structure>
            <structure p="28">This is a false position; and I presume has grown out of the
                never-forgotten distinction of male and female. <religion r_christianity="Jehovah"
                        ><s_theory s_natural_rights="religious justification">The woman who goes
                        forth, clad in the panoply of God, to stem the tide of iniquity and misery,
                        which she beholds rolling through our land, goes not forth to her labor of
                        love as a female. She goes as the dignified messenger of Jehovah, and all
                        she does and says must be done and said irrespective of sex.</s_theory>
                </religion>She is in duty bound to communicate with all, who are able and willing to
                aid her in saving her fellow creatures, both men and women, from that destruction
                which awaits them. </structure>
            <structure p="29"><religion r_quaker="Emulating Jesus">So far from woman losing any
                    thing of the purity of her mind, by visiting the wretched victims of vice in
                    their miserable abodes, by talking with them, or of them, she becomes more and
                    more elevated and refined in her feelings and views. While laboring to cleanse
                    the minds of others from the malaria of moral pollution, her own heart becomes
                    purified, and her soul rises to nearer communion with her God. Such a woman is
                    infinitely better qualified to fulfil the duties of a wife and a mother, than
                    the woman whose false delicacy leads her to shun her fallen sister and brother,
                    and shrink from naming those sins which she knows exist, but which she is too
                    fastidious to labor by deed and by word to exterminate.</religion> Such a woman
                feels when she enters upon the marriage relation, that God designed that relation
                not to debase her to a level with the animal creation, but to increase the happiness
                and dignity of his creatures. Such a woman comes to the important task of training
                her children in the nurture and admonition of the Lord, with a soul filled with the
                greatness of the beings committed to her charge. <religion
                    r_quaker="Women have a duty or inclination to teach their children as an 'image of God'"
                    >She sees in her children, creatures bearing the image of God; and she
                    approaches them with reverence, and treats them at all times as moral and
                    accountable beings. Her own mind being purified and elevated, she instils into
                    her children that genuine religion which induces them to keep the commandments
                    of God. Instead of ministering with ceaseless care to their sensual appetites,
                    she teaches them to be temperate in all things. She can converse with her
                    children on any subject relating to their duty to God, can point their attention
                    to those vices which degrade and brutify human nature, without in the least
                    defiling her own mind or theirs. She views herself, and teaches her children to
                    regard themselves as moral beings; and in all their intercourse with their
                    fellow men, to lose the animal nature of man and woman, in the recognition of
                    that immortal mind wherewith Jehovah has blessed and enriched them. </religion>
            </structure>
            <structure p="sig4">Thine in the bonds of womanhood, </structure><structure sig="Grimke"
                > Sarah M. Grimke </structure>. </structure>
        <!-- End letter 4-->
        <structure le="5">
            <structure header="5">LETTER V</structure>. <structure subhead="5">CONDITION IN ASIA AND
                AFRICA.</structure>
            <structure date="August 4th, 1837"><setting>Groton</setting>, 8th Mo. 4th,
                1837</structure>. <structure p="30">My Dear Sister,—I design to devote this letter
                to a <identity race="nonwestern, Asian and African">brief examination of the
                    condition of women in Asia and Africa</identity>. I believe it will be found
                that men, in the exercise of their usurped dominion over woman, have almost
                invariably done one of two things. <power_system
                    p_patriarchy="Men in all countries have ">They have either made slaves of the
                    creatures whom God designed to be their companions and their coadjutors in every
                    moral and intellectual improvement, or they have dressed them like dolls, and
                    used them as toys to amuse their hours of recreation.</power_system>
            </structure>
            <structure p="31"><power_system p_social="Human trafficking or trade">I shall commence
                    by stating the degrading practice of SELLING WOMEN, which we find prevalent in
                    almost all the Eastern nations.</power_system></structure>
            <structure p="32">Among the <identity race="Jewish">Jews</identity>,— </structure>
            <structure q="uncredited">
                <structure p="33"> ‘Whoever wished for a wife must pay the parents for her, or
                    perform a stipulated period of service; sometimes the parties were solemnly
                    betrothed in childhood, and the price of the bride stipulated.’ </structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="34">In <identity nationality="Babylonian, or Middle Eastern"
                    >Babylon</identity>, they had a yearly custom of a peculiar kind. </structure>
            <structure q="uncredited">
                <structure p="35">‘In every district, three men, respectable for their virtue, were
                    chosen to conduct all the marriageable girls to the public assembly. Here they
                    were put up at auction by the public crier, while the magistrate presided over
                    the sales. <power_system p_social="Women monetarily valued by appearance">The
                        most beautiful were sold first, and the rich contended eagerly for a choice.
                        The most ugly, or deformed girl was sold next in succession to the
                        handsomest, and assigned to any person who would take her with the least sum
                        of money. The price given for the beautiful was divided into dowries for the
                        homely.’</power_system></structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="36">Two things may here be noticed; first, the value set upon personal
                charms, just as a handsome horse commands a high price; and second, the utter
                disregard which is manifested towards the feelings of woman.</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited">
                <structure p="37">‘In no part of the world does the condition of women appear more
                    dreary than in <identity nationality="India">Hindostan</identity>. The arbitrary
                    power of a father disposes of them in childhood. When they are married, their
                    husbands have despotic control over them; if unable to support them, they can
                    lend or sell them to a neighbor, and in the Hindoo rage for gambling, wives and
                    children are frequently staked and lost. If they survive their husbands, they
                    must pay implicit obedience to the oldest son; if they have no sons, the nearest
                    male relation holds them in subjection; and if there happen to be no kinsmen,
                    they must be dependent on the chief of the tribe.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="38">Even the <identity nationality="English">English</identity>, who are
                numerous in Hindostan, have traded in women. </structure>
            <structure q="uncredited"><structure p="39">‘India has been a great marriage market, on
                    account of the emigration of young enterprising Englishmen, without a
                    corresponding number of women. <power_system
                        p_race="Non-Enlish women trafficked by Englishmen"
                        p_class="Women from colonized countries subject to English violence">Some
                        persons actually imported women to the British settlements, in order to sell
                        them to rich Europeans, or nabobs, who would give a good price for
                        them.</power_system>
                    <power_system p_class="Lower class women more susceptible to being trafficked"
                        >How the importers acquired a right thus to dispose of them is not
                        mentioned; it is probable that the women themselves, from extreme poverty,
                        or some other cause, consented to become articles of speculation, upon
                        consideration of receiving a certain remuneration.</power_system> In
                    September, 1818, the following advertisement appeared in the Calcutta
                    Advertiser:</structure>
                <structure q="Calcutta Advertiser">
                    <structure p="40">FEMALES RAFFLED FOR</structure>. </structure>
                <structure p="41">Be it known, that six fair pretty young ladies, with two sweet
                    engaging children, lately imported from Europe, having the roses of health
                    blooming on their cheeks, and joy sparkling in their eyes, possessing amiable
                    tempers and highly accomplished, whom the most indifferent cannot behold without
                    rapture, are to be raffled for next door to the British gallery.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="42"><power_system p_patriarchy="Women subject to men's indulgences">The
                    enemy of all good could not have devised a better means of debasing an immortal
                    creature, than by turning her into a saleable commodity; and hence we find that
                    wherever this custom prevails, woman is regarded as a mere machine to answer the
                    purposes of domestic combat or sensual indulgence, or to gratify the taste of
                    her oppressor by a display of personal attractions.</power_system></structure>
            <structure q="James Beattie's 'The Minstrel'">
                <structure p="43"> ‘Weighed in the balance with a tyrant’s gold, Though nature cast
                    her in a heavenly mould.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="44">I shall now take a brief survey of the EMPLOYMENTS of women in Asia
                and Africa. In doing this, I have two objects in view; first to show, that women are
                capable of acquiring as great physical power as men, and secondly to show, that they
                have been more or less the victims of oppression and contempt.</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited">
                <structure p="45">‘The occupations of the ancient Jewish women were laborious. They
                    spent their time in spinning and weaving cloth for garments, and for the
                    covering of the tents, in cooking the food, tending the flocks, grinding the
                    corn, and drawing water from the wells.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="46">Of <identity nationality="Turkish">Trojan</identity> women we know
                little, but we find that—</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited">
                <structure p="47">‘Andromache, though a princess and well beloved by her husband,
                    fed and took care of the horses of Hector.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="48">So in <identity nationality="Turkish">Persia</identity>, <class
                    middle="women">women of the middling class see that proper care is taken of the
                    horses. They likewise do all the laborious part of the house
                work.</class></structure>
            <structure q="uncredited">
                <structure p="49"> ‘The <identity race="Hindu or Indian">Hindoo</identity> women are
                        <class economic="Women's work varies based on husband's occupation/class"
                        >engaged in every variety of occupation, according to the caste of their
                        husbands.</class> They cultivate the land, make baskets and mats, bring
                    water in jars, carry manure and various other articles to market in baskets on
                    their heads, cook food, tend children, weave cloth, reel thread and wind
                    cocoons.’</structure>
                <structure p="50">‘The <identity nationality="Tibet">Thibetian</identity> women of
                    the <class lower="low-middle" middle="low-middle">laboring classes</class> are
                    inured to a great deal of toil. They plant, weed, reap, and thresh grain, and
                    are exposed to the roughest weather, while their indolent husbands are perhaps
                    living at their ease.’</structure>
                <structure p="51">‘<class lower="lower">Females of the lower classes</class> among
                    the <identity nationality="Chinese">Chinese</identity> endure as much labor and
                    fatigue as the men. A wife sometimes drags the plough in rice fields with an
                    infant tied upon her back, while her husband performs the less arduous task of
                    holding the plough.’</structure>
                <structure p="52">‘The <identity race="Central/Northeast Asia">Tartar</identity> <power_system p_patriarchy="women do majority of work">women in general perform a greater share of labor than
                    the men; for it is a prevalent opinion that they were sent into the world for no
                    other purpose, but to be useful and convenient SLAVES to the stronger sex.</power_system>’
                    ‘Among some of the Tartar tribes of the present day, females manage a horse,
                    hurl a javelin, hunt wild animals, and fight an enemy as well as the
                    men.’</structure>
                <structure p="53">‘In the island of <identity nationality="Indonesian">Sumatra</identity>, <power_system p_patriarchy="women do majority of work">the women do all the work, while their
                    husbands lounge in idleness, playing on the flute, with wreaths of globe
                    amaranth on their heads, or racing with each other, without saddle or stirrup,
                    or hunting deer, or gambling away their wives, their children, or themselves.
                    The Battas consider their wives and children as slaves, and sell them whenever
                    they choose.</power_system>’</structure>
                <structure p="54">‘The <identity race="North African Arabs">Moors</identity> are indolent to excess. <power_system p_patriarchy="women do majority of work">They lie whole days upon their
                    mats, sleeping and smoking, while the women and slaves perform all the labor.</power_system>
                    Owing to their uncleanly habits, they are much infested with vermin; and as they
                    consider it beneath their dignity to remove this annoyance, the task is imposed
                    on the women. <power_system p_social="Physical overpowering">They are very impatient and tyrannical, and for the slightest
                    offence beat their wives most cruelly.</power_system>’</structure>
            </structure>
            <!-- end large quote section -->
            <structure p="55"><religion r_christianity="Jehovah, Eve">In looking over the condition of woman as delineated in this letter,
                how amply do we find the prophecy of Jehovah to Eve fulfilled, ‘Thy husband will
                rule over thee.’</religion> And yet we perceive that where the physical strength of woman is
                called into exercise, there is no inferiority even in this respect; she performs the
                labor, while man enjoys what are termed the pleasures of life.</structure>
            <structure p="56">I have thought it necessary to adduce various proofs of my assertion,
                that men have always in some way regarded women as mere instruments of selfish
                gratification; and hope this sorrowful detail of the wrongs of woman will not be
                tedious to thee</structure>. <structure p="sig5">Thine in the bonds of
                womanhood,</structure> Sarah M. Grimke. </structure>
        <!-- End letter 5 -->
        <structure le="6">
            <structure header="6">LETTER VI. </structure>
            <structure subhead="6">WOMEN IN ASIA AND AFRICA. </structure>
            <structure date="August 15th, 1837"><setting>Groton</setting>, 8th Mo. 15th, 1837. </structure>
            <structure p="57">Dear Friend,—In pursuing the history of woman in different ages and
                countries, it will be necessary to exhibit her in all the various situations in
                which she has been placed.</structure>
            <structure p="58">We find her sometimes filling the throne, and exercising the functions
                of royalty. The name of Semiramis is familiar to every reader of ancient history.
                She succeeded Ninus in the government of the Assyrian empire; and to render her name
                immortal, built the city of Babylon. Two millions of men were constantly employed
                upon it. Certain dykes built by order of this queen, to defend the city from
                inundations, are spoken of as admirable.</structure>
            <structure p="59">Nicotris, wife of Nabonadius, the Evil-Merodach of Scripture, was a
                woman of great endowments. While her husband indulged in a life of ease and
                pleasure, she managed the affairs of state with wisdom and prudence.</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited">
                <structure p="60">‘Zenobia queen of Palmyra and the East, is the most remarkable
                    among Asiatic women. Her genius struggled with and overcame all the obstacles
                    presented by oriental laws and customs. She knew the Latin, Greek, Syriac, and
                    Egyptian languages; and had drawn up for her own use an abridgement of oriental
                    history. She was the companion and friend of her husband, and accompanied him on
                    his hunting excursions with eagerness and courage equal to his own. She despised
                    the effeminacy of a covered carriage, and often appeared on horseback in
                    military costume. Sometimes she marched several miles on foot, at the head of
                    the troops. Having revenged the murder of her husband, she ascended the throne,
                    and for five years governed Palmyra, Syria, and the East, with wonderful
                    steadiness and wisdom.’</structure>
                <structure p="61">‘Previous to the introduction of Mohammedism into Java, women
                    often held the highest offices of government; and when the chief of a district
                    dies, it is even now not uncommon for the widow to retain the authority that
                    belonged to her deceased husband.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="62">Other instances might be adduced to prove that there is no natural
                inferiority in woman. Not that I approve of woman’s holding the reins of government
                over man. I maintain that they are equal, and that God never invested fallen man
                with unlimited power over his fellow man; and I rejoice that circumstances have
                prevented woman from being more deeply involved in the guilt which appears to be
                inseparable from political affairs. The few instances which I have mentioned prove
                that intellect is not sexed; and doubtless if woman had not almost universally been
                depressed and degraded, the page of history would have exhibited as many eminent
                statesmen and politicians among women as men. We are much in the situation of the
                slave. Man has asserted and assumed authority over us. He has, by virtue of his
                power, deprived us of the advantages of improvement which he has lavishly bestowed
                upon himself, and then, after having done all he can to take from us the means of
                proving our equality, and our capability of mental cultivation, he throws upon us
                the burden of proof that God created man and woman equal, and endowed them, without
                any reference to sex, with intelligence and responsibilities, as rational and
                accountable beings. Hence in Hindostan, even women of the higher classes are
                forbidden to read or write; because the Hindoos think it would inevitably spoil them
                for domestic life, and assuredly bring some great misfortune upon them. May we not
                trace to the same feeling, the disadvantages under which women labor even in this
                country, for want of an education, which would call into exercise the powers of her
                mind, and fortify her soul with those great moral principles by which she would be
                qualified to fill every department in social, domestic and religious life with
                dignity?</structure>
            <structure p="63">In Hindostan, the evidence of women is not received in a court of
                justice. </structure>
            <structure p="64">In Burmah, their testimony is not deemed equal to that of a man, and
                they are not allowed to ascend the steps of a court of justice, but are obliged to
                give their testimony outside of the building.</structure>
            <structure p="65">In Siberia, women are not allowed to step across the foot-prints of
                men, or reindeer; they are not allowed to eat with men, or to partake of particular
                dainties. Among many tribes, they seem to be regarded as impure, unholy
                beings.</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited">
                <structure p="66">‘The Mohammedan law forbids pigs, dogs, women and other impure
                    animals to enter a mosque; and the hour of prayers must not be proclaimed by a
                    female, a madman, a drunkard, or a decrepit person.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="67">Here I am reminded of the resemblance between the situation of women
                in heathen and Mohammedan countries, and our brethren and sisters of color in this
                Christian land, where[Pg 35] they are despised and cast out as though they were
                unclean. And on precisely the same ground, because they are said to be
                inferior.</structure>
            <structure p="68">The treatment of women as wives is almost uniformly the same in all
                heathen countries.</structure>
            <structure p="69">The ancient Lydians are the only exception that I have met with, and
                the origin of their peculiar customs is so much obscured by fable, that it is
                difficult to ascertain the truth. Probably they arose from some great benefit
                conferred on the state by women.</structure>
            <structure p="70">Among the Druses who reside in the mountains of the Anti Libanus, a
                wife is often divorced on the slightest pretext. If she ask her husband’s permission
                to go out, and he says,—‘Go,’ without adding ‘but come back again,’ she is
                divorced.</structure>
            <structure p="71">In Siberia, it is considered a wife’s duty to obey the most capricious
                and unreasonable demands of her husband, without one word of expostulation or
                inquiry. If her master be dissatisfied with the most trifling particular in her
                conduct, he tears the cap or veil from her head, and this constitutes a
                divorce.</structure>
            <structure p="72">A Persian woman, under the dominion of the kindest master, is treated
                much in the same manner as a favorite animal. To vary her personal graces for his
                pleasure, is the sole end and aim of her existence. As moral or intellectual beings,
                it would be better for them to be among the dead than the living. The mother
                instructs her daughter in all the voluptuous coquetry, by which she herself acquired
                precarious ascendency over her absolute master; but all that is truly estimable in
                female character is utterly neglected. </structure>
            <structure p="73">Hence we find women extravagantly fond of adorning their persons.
                Regarded as instruments of pleasure, they have been degraded into mere animals, and
                have found their own gratification principally in the indulgence of personal vanity,
                because their external charms procured for them, at least a temporary ascendency
                over those, who held in their hands the reins of government. A few instances must
                suffice, or I shall exceed the limits I have prescribed to myself in this letter. </structure>
            <structure p="74">During the magnificent prosperity of Israel, marriages were conducted
                with great pomp; and with the progress of luxury and refinement, women became
                expensive, rather than profitable in a pecuniary point of view. Hence probably arose
                the custom of wealthy parents giving a handsome dowry with their daughters. On the
                day of the nuptials, the bride was conducted by her female relations to the bath,
                where she was anointed with the choicest perfumes, her hair perfumed and braided,
                her eyebrows deepened with black powder, and the tips of her fingers tinged with
                rose color. She was then arrayed in a marriage robe of brilliant color; the girdle
                and bracelets were more or less costly.</structure>
            <structure p="75">Notwithstanding the Chinese women have no opportunity to rival each
                other in the conquest of hearts, they are nevertheless very fond of ornaments.
                Bunches of silver or gilt flowers are always interspersed among their ringlets, and
                sometimes they wear the Chinese phœnix made of silver gilt. It moves with the
                slightest motion of the wearer, and the spreading tail forms a glittering aigrette
                on the middle of the head, and the wings wave over the front. Yet a Chinese ballad
                says,—The pearls and precious stones, the silk and gold with which a coquette so
                studiously bedecks herself, are a transparent varnish which makes all her defects
                the more apparent.</structure>
            <structure p="76">The Moorish women have generally a great passion for ornament. They
                decorate their persons with heavy gold ear-rings, necklaces of amber, coral and
                gold; gold bracelets; gold chains and silver bells for the ankles; rings on the
                fingers, &amp;c. &amp;c. The poorer class wear glass beads around the head, and curl
                the hair in large ringlets. Men are proud of having their wives handsomely dressed. </structure>
            <structure p="77">The Moors are not peculiar in this fancy. Christian men still admire
                women who adorn their persons to gratify the lust of the eye and the pride of life.
                Women, says a Brahminical expositor, are characterized by an inordinate love of
                jewels, fine clothes, &amp;c. &amp;c. I cannot deny this charge, but it is only one
                among many instances, wherein men have reproached us with those very faults and
                vices which their own treatment has engendered. Is it any matter of surprise that
                women, when unnaturally deprived of the means of cultivating their minds, of objects
                which would elevate and refine their passions and affections, should seek
                gratification in the toys and the trifles which now too generally engage their
                attention?</structure>
            <structure p="78">I cannot close this, without acknowledging the assistance and
                information I have derived, and shall continue to derive on this part of my subject,
                from a valuable work entitled ‘Condition of Women, by Lydia M. Child.’ It is worth
                the perusal of every one who is interested in the subject. </structure>
            <structure p="sig6">Thine in the bonds of womanhood,</structure>
            <structure sig="Grimke"> Sarah M. Grimke </structure>. </structure>
        <!-- End letter 6 -->
        <structure le="7">
            <structure header="7">LETTER VII. </structure>
            <structure subhead="7">CONDITION IN SOME PARTS OF EUROPE AND AMERICA. </structure>
            <structure date="August 22nd, 1837">
                <setting>Brookline</setting>, 8th Mo., 22d, 1837. </structure>
            <structure p="79">Dear Sister,—I now come to the consideration of the condition of woman
                in Europe.—In this portion of the world, she does not appear to have been as
                uniformly or as deeply debased, as in Eastern countries; yet we shall find little in
                her history which can yield us satisfaction, when we regard the high station she was
                designed to occupy as a moral and intellectual being.</structure>
            <structure p="80">In Greece, if we may judge from what Eustathius says, ‘women should
                keep within doors, and there talk,’—we may conclude, that in general their
                occupations were chiefly domestic. Thucydides also declares, that ‘she was the best
                woman, of whom the least was said, either of good or of harm.’ The heathen
                philosophers doubtless wished to keep woman in her ‘appropriate sphere;’ and we find
                our clerical brethren of the present day re-echoing these pagan sentiments, and
                endeavoring to drive woman from the field of moral labor and intellectual culture,
                to occupy her talents in the pursuit of those employments which will enable her to
                regale the palate of her lord with the delicacies of the table, and in every
                possible way minister to his animal comfort and gratification. In my humble opinion,
                woman has long enough subserved the interests of man; and in the spirit of
                self-sacrifice, submitted almost without remonstrance to his oppression; and now
                that her attention is solicited to the subject of her rights, her privileges and her
                duties, I would entreat her to double her diligence in the performance of all her
                obligations as a wife, a mother, a sister, and a daughter. Let us remember that our
                claim to stand on perfect equality with our brethren, can only be substantiated by a
                scrupulous attention to our domestic duties, as well as by aiding in the great work
                of moral reformation—a work which is now calling for the energies and consecrated
                powers of every man and woman who desires to see the Redeemer’s kingdom established
                on earth. That man must indeed be narrow minded, and can have but a poor conception
                of the power of moral truth on the female heart, who supposes that a correct view of
                her own rights can make woman less solicitous to fill up every department of duty.
                If it should have this effect, it must be because she has not taken a comprehensive
                view of the whole subject. </structure>
            <structure p="81">In the history of Rome, we find a little spot of sunshine in the
                valley where woman has been destined to live, unable from her lowly situation to
                take an expansive view of that field of moral and mental improvement, which she
                should have been busy in cultivating.</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited"><structure p="82">‘In the earliest and best days of Rome, the
                    first magistrates and generals of armies ploughed their own fields, and threshed
                    their own grain. Integrity, industry and simplicity, were the prevailing virtues
                    of the times; and the character of woman was, as it always must be, graduated in
                    a degree by that of man. Columella says, Roman husbands, having completed the
                    labors of the day, entered their houses free from all care, and there enjoyed
                    perfect repose. There reigned union and concord and industry, supported by
                    mutual affections. The most beautiful woman depended for distinction on her
                    economy and endeavors to assist in crowning her husband’s diligence with
                    prosperity. All was in common between them; nothing was thought to belong more
                    to one than another. The wife by her assiduity and activity within doors,
                    equalled and seconded the industry and labor of her husband.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="83">In the then state of the world, we may conclude from this description,
                that woman enjoyed as much happiness as was consistent with that comparatively
                unimproved condition of our species; but now a new and vast sphere of usefulness is
                opened to her, and she is pressed by surrounding circumstances to come up to the
                help of the Lord against the giant sins which desolate our beloved country. Shall
                woman shrink from duty in this exigency, and retiring within her own domestic
                circle, delight herself in the abundance of her own selfish enjoyments? Shall she
                rejoice in her home, her husband, her children, and forget her brethren and sisters
                in bondage, who know not what it is to call a spot of earth their own, whose
                husbands and wives are torn from them by relentless tyrants, and whose children are
                snatched from their arms by their unfeeling task-masters, whenever interest, or
                convenience, tempts them to this sacrilegious act? Shall woman disregard the
                situation of thousands of her fellow creatures, who are the victims of intemperance
                and licentiousness, and retreating to the privacy of her own comfortable home, be
                satisfied that her whole duty is performed, when she can exhibit ‘her children well
                clad and smiling, and her table neatly spread with wholesome provisions?’ Shall she,
                because ‘her house is her home,’ refuse her aid and her sympathy to the down trodden
                slave, to the poor unhappy outcasts who are deprived of those blessings which she so
                highly prizes? Did God give her those blessings to steel her heart to the sufferings
                of her fellow creatures? Did he grant her the possession of husband and children, to
                dry up the fountains of feeling for those who know not the consolations of
                tenderness and reciprocal affection? Ah no! for every such blessing, God demands a
                grateful heart; and woman must be recreant to her duty, if she can quietly sit down
                in the enjoyments of her own domestic circle, and not exert herself to procure the
                same happiness for others.</structure>
            <structure p="84">But it is said woman has a mighty weapon in secret prayer. She has, I
                acknowledge, in common with man; but the woman who prays in sincerity for the
                regeneration of this guilty world, will accompany her prayers by her labors. A
                friend of mine remarked—‘I was sitting in my chamber, weeping over the miseries of
                the slave, and putting up my petitions for his deliverance from bondage; when in the
                midst of my meditations, it occurred to me that my tears, unaided by effort, could
                never melt the chain of the slave. I must be up and doing.’ She is now an active
                abolitionist—her prayers and her works go hand in hand</structure>. <structure
                p="85">I am here reminded of what a slave once said to his master, a Methodist
                minister. The slaveholder inquired, ‘How did you like my sermon to-day?’ ‘Very good,
                master, but it did not preach me free.</structure>’ <structure p="86">Oh, my
                sisters, suffer me to entreat you to assert your privileges, and to perform your
                duties as moral beings. Be not dismayed at the ridicule of man; it is a weapon
                worthy only of little minds, and is employed by those who feel that they cannot
                convince our judgment. Be not alarmed at contumely, or scorn; we must expect this. I
                pray that we may meet it with forbearance and love; and that nothing may drive us
                from the performance of our high and holy duties. Let us ‘cease from man, whose
                breath is in his nostrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of?’ and press forward
                in all the great moral enterprises of the age, leaning only on the arm of our
                Beloved. </structure>
            <structure p="87">But I must return to the subject I commenced with, viz. the condition
                of woman in Europe.</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited">
                <structure p="88">‘The northern nations bore a general resemblance to each other.
                    War and hunting were considered the only honorable occupations for men, and all
                    other employments were left to women and slaves. Even the Visigoths, on the
                    coasts of Spain, left their fields and flocks to the care of women. The people
                    who inhabit the vast extent of country between the Black sea and the North sea,
                    are divided into various distinct races. The women are generally very
                    industrious; even in their walks, they carry a portable distaff, and spin every
                    step of the way. Both Croatian and Walachian women perform all the agricultural
                    operations in addition to their own domestic concerns.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="89">Speaking of the Morlachian women, M. Fortis says, ‘Being treated like
                beasts of burden, and expected to endure submissively every species of hardship,
                they naturally become very dirty and careless in their habits.’</structure>
            <structure p="90">The Cossack women afford a contrast to this disgusting picture. They
                are very cleanly and industrious, and in the absence of their husbands, supply their
                places by taking charge of all their usual occupations, in addition to their own. It
                is rare for a Cossack woman not to know some trade, such as dyeing cloth, tanning
                leather, &amp;c. </structure>
            <structure p="91">The condition of Polish and Russian serfs in modern times is about the
                same. The Polish women have scarcely clothing enough for decency, and they are
                subjected to great hardships and privations. ‘In Russia, women have been seen paving
                the streets, and performing other similar drudgery. In Finland, they work like
                beasts of burden, and may be seen for hours in snow water, up to the middle, tugging
                at boats and sledges.’ </structure>
            <structure p="82">In Flanders and in France, women are engaged in performing laborious
                tasks; and even in England, it is not unusual to see them scraping up manure from
                the streets with their hands, and gathering it into baskets. </structure>
            <structure p="83">In Greece, even now the women plough and carry heavy burdens, while
                the lordly master of the family may be seen walking before them without any
                incumbrance.[1] </structure>
            <structure p="84">Generally speaking, however, there is much more comparative equality
                of labor between the sexes in Europe than among the Orientals. </structure>
            <structure p="85">I shall close this letter with a brief survey of the condition of
                women among the Aborigines of America.</structure>
            <structure>‘Before America was settled by Europeans, it was inhabited by Indian tribes,
                which greatly resembled each other in the treatment of their women. Every thing,
                except war and hunting, was considered beneath the dignity of man.—During long and
                wearisome marches, women were obliged to carry children, provisions and hammocks on
                their shoulders; they had the sole care of the horses and dogs, cut wood, pitched
                the tents, raised the corn, and made the clothing. When the husband killed game, he
                left it by a tree in the forest, returned home, and sent his wife several miles in
                search of it. In most of the tribes, women were not allowed to eat and drink with
                men, but stood and served them, and then ate what they left.’ </structure>
            <structure p="86">The following affecting anecdote may give some idea of the sufferings
                of these women:</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited"><structure p="87">‘Father Joseph reproved a female savage for
                    destroying her infant daughter. She replied, “I wish my mother had thus
                    prevented the manifold sufferings I have endured. Consider, father, our
                    deplorable situation. Our husbands go out to hunt; we are dragged along with one
                    infant at our breast, and another in a basket. Though tired with long walking,
                    we are not allowed to sleep when we return, but must labor all night in grinding
                    maize and making chica for them.—They get drunk and beat us, draw us by the hair
                    of the head, and tread us under foot. Would to God my mother had put me under
                    ground the moment I was born.”’ </structure></structure>
            <structure p="88">In Greenland, the situation of woman is equally deplorable. The men
                hunt bears and catch seals; but when they have towed their booty to land, they would
                consider it a disgrace to help the women drag it home, or skin and dress it. They
                often stand and look idly on, while their wives are staggering beneath the load that
                almost bends them to the earth. The women are cooks, butchers, masons, curriers,
                shoemakers and tailors. They will manage a boat in the roughest seas, and will often
                push off from the shore in the midst of a storm, that would make the hardiest
                European sailor tremble. </structure>
            <structure p="89">The page of history teems with woman’s wrongs, and it is wet with
                woman’s tears.—For the sake of my degraded sex every where, and for the sake of my
                brethren, who suffer just in proportion as they place woman lower in the scale of
                creation than man, lower than her Creator placed her, I entreat my sisters to arise
                in all the majesty of moral power, in all the dignity of immortal beings, and plant
                themselves, side by side, on the platform of human rights, with man, to whom they
                were designed to be companions, equals and helpers in every good word and
                work.</structure>
            <structure p="sig7">Thine in the bonds of womanhood </structure>
            <structure sig="Grimke"> Sarah M. Grimke </structure>. <structure fnote="1">FOOTNOTES:
                [1] Since the preceding letters were in type, I have met with the following account
                in a French work entitled ‘De l’education des meres de famille ou de la civilization
                du Genre Humain par les femmes,’ printed at Brussels in 1837. ‘The periodicals have
                lately published the following circumstance from the journal of an English
                physician, who travelled in the East. He visited a slave market, where he saw about
                twenty Greek women half naked, lying on the ground waiting for a purchaser. One of
                them attracted the attention of an old Turk. The barbarian examined her shoulders,
                her legs, her ears, her mouth, her neck, with the minutest care, just as a horse is
                examined, and during the inspection, the merchant praised the beauty of her eyes,
                the elegance of her shape, and other perfections; he protested that the poor girl
                was but thirteen years of age, &amp;c. After a severe scrutiny and some dispute
                about the price, she was sold body and soul for 1375 francs. The soul, it is true,
                was accounted of little value in the bargain. The unfortunate creature, half
                fainting in the arms of her mother, implored help in the most touching accents, but
                it availed nothing.—This infernal scene passed in Europe in 1829, only 600 leagues
                from Paris and London, the two capitals of the human species, and at the time in
                which I write, it is the living history of two thirds of the inhabitants of the
                earth.’</structure>
        </structure>
        <!--End letter 7 -->
        <structure le="8">
            <structure header="8">LETTER VIII.</structure>
            <structure subhead="8">ON THE CONDITION OF WOMEN IN THE UNITED STATES</structure>.
                <structure date="1837"><setting>Brookline</setting>, 1837.</structure>
            <structure p="90">My dear Sister,—I have now taken a brief survey of the condition of
                woman in various parts of the world. I regret that my time has been so much occupied
                by other things, that I have been unable to bestow that attention upon the subject
                which it merits, and that my constant change of place has prevented me from having
                access to books, which might probably have assisted me in this part of my work. I
                hope that the principles I have asserted will claim the attention of some of my sex,
                who may be able to bring into view, more thoroughly than I have done, the situation
                and degradation of woman. I shall now proceed to make a few remarks on the condition
                of women in my own country.</structure>
            <structure p="91">During the early part of my life, my lot was cast among the
                butterflies of the fashionable world; and of this class of women, I am constrained
                to say, both from experience and observation, that their education is miserably
                deficient; that they are taught to regard marriage as the one thing needful, the
                only avenue to distinction; hence to attract the notice and win the attentions of
                men, by their external charms, is the chief business of fashionable girls. They
                seldom think that men will be allured by intellectual acquirements, because they
                find, that where any mental superiority exists, a woman is generally shunned and
                regarded as stepping out of her ‘appropriate sphere,’ which, in their view, is to
                dress, to dance, to set out to the best possible advantage her person, to read the
                novels which inundate the press, and which do more to destroy her character as a
                rational creature, than any thing else. Fashionable women regard themselves, and are
                regarded by men, as pretty toys or as mere instruments of pleasure; and the vacuity
                of mind, the heartlessness, the frivolity which is the necessary result of this
                false and debasing estimate of women, can only be fully understood by those who have
                mingled in the folly and wickedness of fashionable life; and who have been called
                from such pursuits by the voice of the Lord Jesus, inviting their weary and heavy
                laden souls to come unto Him and learn of Him, that they may find something worthy
                of their immortal spirit, and their intellectual powers; that they may learn the
                high and holy purposes of their creation, and consecrate themselves unto the service
                of God; and not, as is now the case, to the pleasure of man.</structure>
            <structure p="92">There is another and much more numerous class in this country, who are
                withdrawn by education or circumstances from the circle of fashionable amusements,
                but who are brought up with the dangerous and absurd idea, that marriage is a kind
                of preferment; and that to be able to keep their husband’s house, and render his
                situation comfortable, is the end of her being. Much that she does and says and
                thinks is done in reference to this situation; and to be married is too often held
                up to the view of girls as the sine qua non of human happiness and human existence.
                For this purpose more than for any other, I verily believe the majority of girls are
                trained. This is demonstrated by the imperfect education which is bestowed upon
                them, and the little pains taken to cultivate their minds, after they leave school,
                by the little time allowed them for reading, and by the idea being constantly
                inculcated, that although all household concerns should be attended to with
                scrupulous punctuality at particular seasons, the improvement of their intellectual
                capacities is only a secondary consideration, and may serve as an occupation to fill
                up the odds and ends of time. In most families, it is considered a matter of far
                more consequence to call a girl off from making a pie, or a pudding, than to
                interrupt her whilst engaged in her studies. This mode of training necessarily
                exalts, in their view, the animal above the intellectual and spiritual nature, and
                teaches women to regard themselves as a kind of machinery, necessary to keep the
                domestic engine in order, but of little value as the intelligent companions of
                men.</structure>
            <structure p="93">Let no one think, from these remarks, that I regard a knowledge of
                housewifery as beneath the acquisition of women. Far from it: I believe that a
                complete knowledge of household affairs is an indispensable requisite in a woman’s
                education,—that by the mistress of a family, whether married or single, doing her
                duty thoroughly and understandingly, the happiness of the family is increased to an
                incalculable degree, as well as a vast amount of time and money saved. All I
                complain of is, that our education consists so almost exclusively in culinary and
                other manual operations. I do long to see the time, when it will no longer be
                necessary for women to expend so many precious hours in furnishing ‘a well spread
                table,’ but that their husbands will forego some of their accustomed indulgences in
                this way, and encourage their wives to devote some portion of their time to mental
                cultivation, even at the expense of having to dine sometimes on baked potatoes, or
                bread and butter.</structure>
            <structure p="94">I believe the sentiment expressed by the author of ‘Live and let
                Live,’ is true:</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited"><structure p="95">‘Other things being equal, a woman of the
                    highest mental endowments will always be the best housekeeper, for domestic
                    economy, is a science that brings into action the qualities of the mind, as well
                    as the graces of the heart. A quick perception, judgment, discrimination,
                    decision and order are high attributes of mind, and are all in daily exercise in
                    the well ordering of a family. If a sensible woman, an intellectual woman, a
                    woman of genius, is not a good housewife, it is not because she is either, or
                    all of those, but because there is some deficiency in her character, or some
                    omission of duty which should make her very humble, instead of her indulging in
                    any secret self-complacency on account of a certain superiority, which only
                    aggravates her fault.’</structure></structure>
            <structure p="96">The influence of women over the minds and character of children of
                both sexes, is allowed to be far greater than that of men. This being the case by
                the very ordering of nature, women should be prepared by education for the
                performance of their sacred duties as mothers and as sisters. A late American
                writer,[2] speaking on this subject, says in reference to an article in the
                Westminster Review:</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited"><structure p="97">‘I agree entirely with the writer in the
                    high estimate which he places on female education, and have long since been
                    satisfied, that the subject not only merits, but imperiously demands a thorough
                    reconsideration. The whole scheme must, in my opinion, be reconstructed. The
                    great elements of usefulness and duty are too little attended to. Women ought,
                    in my view of the subject, to approach to the best education now given to men,
                    (I except mathematics and the classics,) far more I believe than has ever yet
                    been attempted. Give me a host of educated, pious mothers and sisters, and I
                    will do more to revolutionize a country, in moral and religious taste, in
                    manners and in social virtues and intellectual cultivation, than I can possibly
                    do in double or treble the time, with a similar host of educated men. I cannot
                    but think that the miserable condition of the great body of the people in all
                    ancient communities, is to be ascribed in a very great degree to the degradation
                    of women.’</structure></structure>
            <structure p="98">There is another way in which the general opinion, that women are
                inferior to men, is manifested, that bears with tremendous effect on the laboring
                class, and indeed on almost all who are obliged to earn a subsistence, whether it be
                by mental or physical exertion—I allude to the disproportionate value set on the
                time and labor of men and of women. A man who is engaged in teaching, can always, I
                believe, command a higher price for tuition than a woman—even when he teaches the
                same branches, and is not in any respect superior to the woman. This I know is the
                case in boarding and other schools with which I have been acquainted, and it is so
                in every occupation in which the sexes engage indiscriminately. As for example, in
                tailoring, a man has twice, or three times as much for making a waistcoat or
                pantaloons as a woman, although the work done by each may be equally good. In those
                employments which are peculiar to women, their time is estimated at only half the
                value of that of men. A woman who goes out to wash, works as hard in proportion as a
                wood sawyer, or a coal heaver, but she is not generally able to make more than half
                as much by a day’s work. The low remuneration which women receive for their work,
                has claimed the attention of a few philanthropists, and I hope it will continue to
                do so until some remedy is applied for this enormous evil. I have known a widow,
                left with four or five children, to provide for, unable to leave home because her
                helpless babes demand her attention, compelled to earn a scanty subsistence, by
                making coarse shirts at 12¹⁄₂ cents a piece, or by taking in washing, for which she
                was paid by some wealthy persons 12¹⁄₂ cents per dozen. All these things evince the
                low estimation in which woman is held. There is yet another and more disastrous
                consequence arising from this unscriptural notion—women being educated, from
                earliest childhood, to regard themselves as inferior creatures, have not that
                self-respect which conscious equality would engender, and hence when their virtue is
                assailed, they yield to temptation with facility, under the idea that it rather
                exalts than debases them, to be connected with a superior being.</structure>
            <structure p="99">There is another class of women in this country, to whom I cannot
                refer, without feelings of the deepest shame and sorrow. I allude to our female
                slaves. Our southern cities are whelmed beneath a tide of pollution; the virtue of
                female slaves is wholly at the mercy of irresponsible tyrants, and women are bought
                and sold in our slave markets, to gratify the brutal lust of those who bear the name
                of Christians. In our slave States, if amid all her degradation and ignorance, a
                woman desires to preserve her virtue unsullied, she is either bribed or whipped into
                compliance, or if she dares resist her seducer, her life by the laws of some of the
                slave States may be, and has actually been sacrificed to the fury of disappointed
                passion. Where such laws do not exist, the power which is necessarily vested in the
                master over his property, leaves the defenceless slave entirely at his mercy, and
                the sufferings of some females on this account, both physical and mental, are
                intense. Mr. Gholson, in the House of Delegates of Virginia, in 1832, said,
                    <structure q="Virginia Delegate Gholson, anti-abolitionist">‘He really had been
                    under the impression that he owned his slaves. He had lately purchased four
                    women and ten children, in whom he thought he had obtained a great bargain; for
                    he supposed they were his own property, as were his brood mares.’ But even if
                    any laws existed in the United States, as in Athens formerly, for the protection
                    of female slaves, they would be null and void, because the evidence of a colored
                    person is not admitted against a white, in any of our Courts of Justice in the
                    slave States. ‘In Athens, if a female slave had cause to complain of any want of
                    respect to the laws of modesty, she could seek the protection of the temple, and
                    demand a change of owners; and such appeals were never discountenanced, or
                    neglected by the magistrate.’</structure> In Christian America, the slave has no
                refuge from unbridled cruelty and lust.</structure>
            <structure p="100">S. A. Forrall, speaking of the state of morals at the South, says,
                ‘Negresses when young and likely, are often employed by the planter, or his friends,
                to administer to their sensual desires. This frequently is a matter of speculation,
                for if the offspring, a mulatto, be a handsome female, 800 or 1000 dollars may be
                obtained for her in the New Orleans market. It is an occurrence of no uncommon
                nature to see a Christian father sell his own daughter, and the brother his own
                sister.’ The following is copied by the N. Y. Evening Star from the Picayune, a
                paper published in New Orleans. ‘A very beautiful girl, belonging to the estate of
                John French, a deceased gambler at New Orleans, was sold a few days since for the
                round sum of $7,000. An ugly-looking bachelor named Gouch, a member of the Council
                of one of the Principalities, was the purchaser. The girl is a brunette; remarkable
                for her beauty and intelligence, and there was considerable contention, who should
                be the purchaser. She was, however, persuaded to accept Gouch, he having made her
                princely promises.’ I will add but one more from the numerous testimonies respecting
                the degradation of female slaves, and the licentiousness of the South. It is from
                the Circular of the Kentucky Union, for the moral and religious improvement of the
                colored race. ‘To the female character among our black population, we cannot allude
                but with feelings of the bitterest shame. A similar condition of moral pollution and
                utter disregard of a pure and virtuous reputation, is to be found only without the
                pale of Christendom. That such a state of society should exist in a Christian
                nation, claiming to be the most enlightened upon earth, without calling forth any
                particular attention to its existence, though ever before our eyes and in our
                families, is a moral phenomenon at once unaccountable and disgraceful.’ Nor does the
                colored woman suffer alone: the moral purity of the white woman is deeply
                contaminated. In the daily habit of seeing the virtue of her enslaved sister
                sacrificed without hesitancy or remorse, she looks upon the crimes of seduction and
                illicit intercourse without horror, and although not personally involved in the
                guilt, she loses that value for innocence in her own, as well as the other sex,
                which is one of the strongest safeguards to virtue. She lives in habitual
                intercourse with men, whom she knows to be polluted by licentiousness, and often is
                she compelled to witness in her own domestic circle, those disgusting and
                heart-sickening jealousies and strifes which disgraced and distracted the family of
                Abraham. In addition to all this, the female slaves suffer every species of
                degradation and cruelty, which the most wanton barbarity can inflict; they are
                indecently divested of their clothing, sometimes tied up and severely whipped,
                sometimes prostrated on the earth, while their naked bodies are torn by the scorpion
                lash.</structure>
            <structure po="2">
                <structure l="1">‘The whip on WOMAN’S shrinking flesh!</structure>
                <structure l="2">Our soil yet reddening with the stains</structure>
                <structure l="3">Caught from her scourging warm and fresh.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="101">Can any American woman look at these scenes of shocking
                licentiousness and cruelty, and fold her hands in apathy, and say, ‘I have nothing
                to do with slavery’? She cannot and be guiltless.</structure>
            <structure p="102">I cannot close this letter, without saying a few words on the
                benefits to be derived by men, as well as women, from the opinions I advocate
                relative to the equality of the sexes. Many women are now supported, in idleness and
                extravagance, by the industry of their husbands, fathers, or brothers, who are
                compelled to toil out their existence, at the counting house, or in the printing
                office, or some other laborious occupation, while the wife and daughters and sisters
                take no part in the support of the family, and appear to think that their sole
                business is to spend the hard bought earnings of their male friends. I deeply regret
                such a state of things, because I believe that if women felt their responsibility,
                for the support of themselves, or their families it would add strength and dignity
                to their characters, and teach them more true sympathy for their husbands, than is
                now generally manifested,—a sympathy which would be exhibited by actions as well as
                words. Our brethren may reject my doctrine, because it runs counter to common
                opinions, and because it wounds their pride; but I believe they would be ‘partakers
                of the benefit’ resulting from the Equality of the Sexes, and would find that woman,
                as their equal, was unspeakably more valuable than woman as their inferior, both as
                a moral and an intellectual being.</structure>
            <structure p="sig8">Thine in the bonds of womanhood, </structure><structure sig="Grimke"
                > Sarah M. Grimke </structure>. FOOTNOTES: [2] Thomas S. Grimke. </structure>
        <!-- End letter 8-->
        <structure le="9">
            <structure header="9">LETTER IX.</structure>
            <structure subhead="9">HEROISM OF WOMEN—WOMEN IN AUTHORITY.</structure>
            <structure date="August 25th, 1837">Brookline, 8th Mo. 25th, 1837.</structure>
            <structure p="103">My Dear Sister,—It seems necessary to glance at the conduct of women
                under circumstances which place them in juxtaposition with men, although I regard it
                as entirely unimportant in proving the moral equality of the sexes; because I
                condemn, in both, the exercise of that brute force which is as contrary to the law
                of God in men as in women; still, as a part of our history, I shall notice some
                instances of courage exhibited by females.</structure>
            <structure q="uncredited"><structure p="104">‘Philippa, wife of Edward III., was the
                    principal cause of the victory gained over the Scots at Neville Cross. In the
                    absence of her husband, she rode among the troops, and exhorted them to “be of
                    good courage.”’ Jane, Countess of Mountfort, and a contemporary of Philippa,
                    likewise possessed a great share of physical courage. The history of Joan of Arc
                    is too familiar to need repetition. During the reign of James II. a singular
                    instance of female intrepidity occurred in Scotland. Sir John Cochrane being
                    condemned to be hung, his daughter twice disguised herself, and robbed the mail
                    that brought his death warrant. In the mean time, his pardon was obtained from
                    the King. Instances might be multiplied, but it is unnecessary. I shall
                    therefore close these proofs of female courage with one more fact. ‘During the
                    revolutionary war, the women shared in the patriotism and bravery of the men.
                    Several individuals carried their enthusiasm so far as to enter the army, where
                    they faced all the perils and fatigues of the camp, until the close of the
                    war.’</structure>
                <structure p="105">When I view my countrywomen in the character of soldiers, or even
                    behold them loading fire arms and moulding bullets for their brethren to destroy
                    men’s lives, I cannot refrain a sigh. I cannot but contrast their conduct at
                    that solemn crisis with the conduct of those women who followed their Lord and
                    Master with unresisting submission, to Calvary’s Mount. With the precepts and
                    example of a crucified Redeemer, who, in that sublime precept, ‘Resist not
                    evil,’ has interdicted to his disciples all war and all violence, and taught us
                    that the spirit of retaliation for injuries, whether in the camp, or at the
                    fire-side, is wholly at variance with the peaceful religion he came to
                    promulgate. How little do we comprehend that simple truth, ‘By this shall all
                    men know that ye are my disciples, if ye have love one to another.’</structure>
            </structure>
            <structure p="106">Women have sometimes distinguished themselves in a way more
                consistent with their duties as moral beings. During the war between the Romans and
                the Sabines, the Sabine women who had been carried off by the Romans, repaired to
                the Sabine camp, dressed in deep mourning, with their little ones in their arms, to
                soften, if possible, the feelings of their parents. They knelt at the feet of their
                relatives; and when Hersilia, the wife of Romulus, described the kindness of their
                husbands, and their unwillingness to be separated from them, their fathers yielded
                to their entreaties, and an alliance was soon agreed upon. In consequence of this
                important service, peculiar privileges were conferred on women by the Romans. Brutus
                said of his wife, ‘I must not answer Portia in the words of Hector, “Mind your
                wheel, and to your maids give law,” for in courage, activity and concern for her
                country’s freedom, she is inferior to none of us.’ After the fatal battle of Cannæ,
                the Roman women consecrated all their ornaments to the service of the state. But
                when the triumvirs attempted to tax them for the expenses of carrying on a civil
                war, they resisted the innovation. They chose Hortensia for their speaker, and went
                in a body to the market-place to expostulate with the magistrates. The triumvirs
                wished to drive them away, but they were compelled to yield to the wishes of the
                people, and give the women a hearing. Hortensia pleaded so well the cause of her
                sisters, who resolved that they would not voluntarily aid in a civil war, that the
                number of women taxed was reduced from 1400 to 400.</structure>
            <structure p="107">In the wars of the Guelphs and the Ghibbelines, the emperor Conrad
                refused all terms of capitulation to the garrison of Winnisberg, but he granted the
                request of the women to pass out in safety with such of their effects as they could
                carry themselves. Accordingly, they issued from the besieged city, each bearing on
                her shoulders a husband, son, father, or brother. They passed unmolested through the
                enemy’s camp, which rung with acclamations of applause.</structure>
            <structure p="108">During our struggle for independence, the women were as exemplary as
                the men in various instances of self-denial: they refused every article of
                decoration for their persons; foreign elegances were laid aside, and they cheerfully
                abstained from luxuries for their tables.</structure>
            <structure p="109">English history presents many instances of women exercising
                prerogatives now denied them. In an action at law, it has been determined that an
                unmarried woman, having a freehold, might vote for members of Parliament; and it is
                recorded that lady Packington returned two. Lady Broughton was keeper of the
                gatehouse prison. And in a much later period, a woman was appointed governor of the
                house of correction at Chelmsford, by order of the court. In the reign of George II.
                the minister of Clerkenwell was chosen by a majority of women. The office of grand
                chamberlain in 1822 was filled by two women; and that of clerk of the crown, in the
                court of king’s bench, has been granted to a female. The celebrated Anne, countess
                of Pembroke, held the hereditary office of sheriff of Westmoreland, and exercised it
                in person, sitting on the bench with the judges.</structure>
            <structure p="110">I need hardly advert to the names of Elizabeth of England, Maria
                Theresa of Germany, Catharine of Russia, and Isabella of Spain, to prove that women
                are capable of swaying the sceptre of royalty. The page of history proves
                incontestibly, not only that they are as well qualified to do so as men, but that
                there has been a comparatively greater proportion of good queens, than of good
                kings; women who have purchased their celebrity by individual strength of
                character.</structure>
            <structure p="111">I mention these women only to prove that intellect is not sexed; that
                strength of mind is not sexed; and that our views about the duties of men and the
                duties of women, the sphere of man and the sphere of woman, are mere arbitrary
                opinions, differing in different ages and countries, and dependant solely on the
                will and judgment of erring mortals.</structure>
            <structure p="112">As moral and responsible beings, men and women have the same sphere
                of action, and the same duties devolve upon both; but no one can doubt that the
                duties of each vary according to circumstances; that a father and a mother, a
                husband and a wife, have sacred obligations resting on them, which cannot possibly
                belong to those who do not sustain these relations. But these duties and
                responsibilities do not attach to them as men and as women, but as parents,
                husbands, and wives.</structure>
            <structure p="sig9"> Thine in the bonds of womanhood</structure>, <structure
                sig="Grimke"> Sarah M. Grimke </structure>. </structure>
        <!-- End letter 9-->
        <structure le="10">
            <structure header="10">LETTER X.</structure>
            <structure subhead="10">INTELLECT OF WOMAN.</structure>
            <structure date="August 1837"><setting>Brookline</setting>, 8th Mo.1837</structure>.
                <structure p="113">My Dear Sister,—It will scarcely be denied, I presume, that, as a
                general rule, <power_system p_patriarchy="men's wishes over women's">men do not
                    desire the improvement of women</power_system>. There are few instances of men
                who are magnanimous enough to be entirely willing that women should know more than
                themselves, on any subjects except dress and cookery; and, indeed, this necessarily
                flows from their assumption of superiority. As they have determined that Jehovah has
                placed woman on a lower platform than man, they of course wish to keep her there;
                and hence the noble faculties of our minds are crushed, and our reasoning powers are
                almost wholly uncultivated.</structure>
            <structure p="114">A writer in the time of Charles I. says—‘She that knoweth how to
                compound a pudding, is more desirable than she who skilfully compounded a poem. A
                female poet I mislike at all times.’ Within the last century, it has been gravely
                asserted that, ‘chemistry enough to keep the pot boiling, and geography enough to
                know the location of the different rooms in her house, is learning sufficient for a
                woman.’ Byron, who was too sensual to conceive of a pure and perfect companionship
                between the sexes, would limit a woman’s library to a Bible and cookery book. I have
                myself heard men, who knew for themselves the value of intellectual culture, say
                they cared very little for a wife who could not make a pudding, and smile with
                contempt at the ardent thirst for knowledge exhibited by some women.</structure>
            <structure p="115">But all this is miserable wit and worse philosophy. It exhibits that
                passion for the gratification of a pampered appetite, which is beneath those who
                claim to be so far above us, and may justly be placed on a par with the policy of
                the slaveholder, who says that men will be better slaves, if they are not permitted
                to learn to read.</structure>
            <structure p="116">In spite, however, of the obstacles which impede the progress of
                women towards that state of high mental cultivation for which her Creator prepared
                her, the tendency towards the universal dissemination of knowledge has had its
                influence on their destinies; and in all ages, a few have surmounted every
                hindrance, and proved, beyond dispute, that they have talents equal to their
                brethren.</structure>
            <structure p="117">Cornelia, the daughter of Scipio Africanus, was distinguished for
                virtue, learning and good sense. She wrote and spoke with uncommon elegance and
                purity. Cicero and Quinctilian bestow high praise upon her letters, and the
                eloquence of her children was attributed to her careful superintendence. This
                reminds me of a remark made by my brother, Thomas S. Grimke, when speaking of the
                importance of women being well educated, that ‘educated men would never make
                educated women, but educated women would make educated men.’ I believe the sentiment
                is correct, because if the wealth of latent intellect among women was fully evolved
                and improved, they would rejoice to communicate to their sons all their own
                knowledge, and inspire them with desires to drink from the fountain of
                literature.</structure>
            <structure p="118">I pass over many interesting proofs of the intellectual powers of
                women; but I must not omit glancing at the age of chivalry, which has been compared
                to a golden thread running through the dark ages. During this remarkable era, women
                who, before this period, had been subject to every species of oppression and
                neglect, were suddenly elevated into deities, and worshipped with a mad fanaticism.
                It is not improbable, however, that even the absurdities of chivalry were beneficial
                to women, as it raised them from that extreme degradation to which they had been
                condemned, and prepared the way for them to be permitted to enjoy some scattered
                rays from the sun of science and literature. As the age of knight-errantry declined,
                men began to take pride in learning, and women shared the advantages which this
                change produced. ‘Women preached in public, supported controversies, published and
                defended theses, filled the chairs of philosophy and law, harangued the popes in
                Latin, wrote Greek and read Hebrew. Nuns wrote poetry, women of rank became divines,
                and young girls publicly exhorted Christian princes to take up arms for the recovery
                of the holy sepulchre. Hypatia, daughter of Theon of Alexandria, succeeded her
                father in the government of the Platonic school, and filled with reputation a seat,
                where many celebrated philosophers had taught. The people regarded her as an oracle,
                and magistrates consulted her in all important cases. No reproach was ever uttered
                against the perfect purity of her manners. She was unembarrassed in large assemblies
                of men, because their admiration was tempered with the most scrupulous respect. In
                the 13th century, a young lady of Bologna pronounced a Latin oration at the age of
                twenty-three. At twenty-six, she took the degree of doctor of laws, and began
                publicly to expound Justinian. At thirty, she was elevated to a professor’s chair,
                and taught the law to a crowd of scholars from all nations. Italy produced many
                learned and gifted women, among whom, perhaps none was more celebrated than Victoria
                Colonna, Marchioness of Pescara. In Spain, Isabella of Rosera converted Jews by her
                eloquent preaching;’ and in England the names of many women, from Lady Jane Gray
                down to Harriet Martineau, are familiar to every reader of history. Of the last
                mentioned authoress, Lord Brougham said that her writings on political economy were
                doing more good than those of any man in England. There is a contemporary of Harriet
                Martineau, who has recently rendered valuable services to her country. She presented
                a memorial to Parliament, stating the dangerous parts of the coast, where
                light-houses were needed, and at her suggestion, several were erected. She keeps a
                life-boat and sailors in her pay, and has been the means of saving many lives.
                Although she has been deprived of the use of her limbs since early childhood, yet
                even when the storm is unusually severe, she goes herself on the beach in her
                carriage, that she may be sure her men perform their duty. She understands several
                languages, and is now engaged in writing a work on the Northern languages of Europe.
                ‘In Germany, the influence of women on literature is considerable, though less
                obvious than in some other countries. Literary families frequently meet at each
                others’ houses, and learned and intelligent women are often the brightest ornaments
                of these social circles.’ France has produced many distinguished women, whose names
                are familiar to every lover of literature. And I believe it is conceded universally,
                that Madame de Stael was intellectually the greatest woman that ever lived. The
                United States have produced several female writers, some of whom have talents of the
                highest order. But women, even in this free republic, do not enjoy all the
                intellectual advantages of men, although there is a perceptible improvement within
                the last ten or twenty years; and I trust there is a desire awakened in my sisters
                for solid acquirements, which will elevate them to their ‘appropriate sphere,’ and
                enable them to ‘adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour in all things.’</structure>
            <structure p="sig10">Thine in the bonds of womanhood</structure>, <structure
                sig="Grimke"> Sarah M. Grimke </structure>. </structure>
        <!-- End letter 10--><structure subhead="17">CONCLUSION</structure>. <structure p="228">I
            have now, my dear sister, completed my series of letters. I am aware, they contain some
            new views; but I believe they are <s_theory s_natural_rights="religious justification"
                >based on the immutable truths of the Bible.</s_theory>
            <religion r_quaker="not condemning people for 'sins'">All I ask for them is, the candid
                and prayerful consideration of Christians. If they strike at some of our bosom sins,
                our deep-rooted prejudices, our long cherished opinions, let us not condemn them on
                that account, but investigate them fearlessly and prayerfully</religion>, and not
            shrink from the examination; because, if they are true, they place heavy
            responsibilities upon women. In throwing them before the public, I have been actuated
            solely by the belief, that if they are acted upon, they will exalt the character and
            enlarge the usefulness of my own sex, and contribute greatly to the happiness and virtue
            of the other. That there is a root of bitterness continually springing up in families
            and troubling the repose of both men and women, must be manifest to even a superficial
            observer; and I believe it is the mistaken notion of the inequality of the sexes.
                <power_system p_patriarchy="'Assumption of superiority'">As there is an assumption
                of superiority on the one part,</power_system>
            <f_theory f_enlightenment_individualism="'individual dignity bestowed by 'Jehovah'"
                >which is not sanctioned by Jehovah, there is an incessant struggle on the other to
                rise to that degree of dignity, which God designed women to possess in common with
                men, and to maintain those rights and exercise those privileges</f_theory>
            <s_theory s_natural_rights="inalienable, rights part of moral nature">which every
                woman’s common sense, apart from the prejudices of education, tells her are
                inalienable; they are a part of her moral nature, and can only cease when her
                immortal mind is extinguished.</s_theory></structure>
        <structure p="229">One word more. I feel that I am calling upon my sex to sacrifice what has
            been, what is still dear to their hearts, the adulation, the flattery, the attentions of
            trifling men. I am asking them to repel these insidious enemies whenever they approach
            them; to manifest by their conduct, that, although they value highly the society of
            pious and intelligent men, they have no taste for idle conversation, and for that silly
            preference which is manifested for their personal accommodation, often at the expense of
            great inconvenience to their male companions. As an illustration of what I mean, I will
            state a fact.</structure>
        <structure p="230">I was traveling lately in a stage coach. A gentleman, who was also a
            passenger, was made sick by riding with his back to the horses. I offered to exchange
            seats, assuring him it did not affect me at all unpleasantly; but he was too polite to
            permit a lady to run the risk of being discommoded. I am sure he meant to be very civil,
            but I really thought it was a foolish piece of civility. This kind of attention
            encourages selfishness in woman, and is only accorded as a sort of quietus, in exchange
            for those rights of which we are deprived. Men and women are equally bound to cultivate
            a spirit of accommodation; but I exceedingly deprecate her being treated like a spoiled
            child, and sacrifices made to her selfishness and vanity. In lieu of these flattering
            but injurious attentions, yielded to her as an inferior, as a mark of benevolence and
            courtesy, I want my sex to claim nothing from their brethren but what their brethren may
            justly claim from them, in their intercourse as Christians. I am persuaded woman can do
            much in this way to elevate her own character. And that we may become duly sensible of
            the dignity of our nature, only a little lower than the angels, and bring forth fruit to
            the glory and honor of Emanuel’s name, is the fervent prayer of</structure>
        <structure p="sig15">Thine in the bonds of womanhood,</structure>
        <structure sig="Grimke"> Sarah M. Grimke </structure>
        <!-- End letter 15 -->
    </main>
</document>
