<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- There are still some anxieties about copyright, so the "Punk Planet" files will be a temporary placeholder !--> 

<?xml-model href="../digmethodsfem_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<document>
    <meta>
        <title>DIY SEX: EARLY TO BED</title>
        <author>Sex Lady Searah</author>
        <publication_date>2004 July-Aug</publication_date>
      
    </meta>
    <main>
        <structure p="paragraph">Ah, <power_system p_patriarchy="blue balls">blue balls</power_system>. As a <identity gender="girl">girl</identity>, 
            I grew up thinking that <power_system p_patriarchy="blue balls">blue balls</power_system> 
            were <power_system p_patriarchy="nothing more than a sad excuse for guys to pressure girls into having sex">
                nothing more than a sad excuse for guys to pressure girls into having sex</power_system>— ’’Gome on baby, you got me all turned on, 
            <power_system p_patriarchy="now you have to fuck me">now you have to fuck me</power_system> or I’ll get <power_system p_patriarchy="blue balls">blue balls</power_system>. ” 
            I figured it was just some made-up term for sexual frustration.  <f_theory f_politicallesbian="Then I became a dyke and I never thought about them again">
                Then I became a dyke and I never thought about them again</f_theory> until I got this letter. So I did a little research and, 
            with some help from the good people of scarleteen.com, I now know that it is indeed a real condition, albeit not a very serious one.</structure>
        
        <structure p="paragraph">The technical term for <power_system p_patriarchy="blue balls">blue balls</power_system> is vasocongestion and it works 
            like this: When a man becomes aroused, the arteries carrying blood to the <identity sexuality="genital">genital</identity> area enlarge, while the veins carrying blood away from the 
            genital area become more constricted than they 
            are when you aren’t turned on. This causes an increase in the amount of blood trapped in the <identity sexuality="penis and testicles">penis and testicles</identity>, which in turn helps 
            you to get your nice, stiff <identity sexuality="erection and swollen balls.">erection and swollen balls.</identity> When you have an <identity sexuality="orgasm">orgasm</identity>, 
            the arteries and veins return to their normal size. 
            If you don’t have an <identity sexuality="orgasm">orgasm</identity>, that blood can get trapped in there and can lead to an achy, sometimes painful feeling in the testicles. 
            The term "blue balls” comes from the bluish tint that <identity sexuality="nuts">nuts</identity> can take on when they are engorged. This pain, however, can usually be easily 
            eradicated by <identity sexuality="masturbating">masturbating</identity> (when’s the last time someone prescribed that for pain?) or, some say, by taking a cold shower or exercising. 
            Obviously, <f_theory f_liberal="this condition is never an excuse to try and talk anyone into touching your dick if they don't want to.">
                this condition is never an excuse to try and talk anyone into touching your dick if they don't want to.</f_theory> You are at absolutely 
            no risk for any damage to your <identity sexuality="cock">cock</identity> and, from what I gather, most guys can easily make themselves come in a matter of minutes, <f_theory f_liberal="so you 
                shouldn’t have to suffer for too long">so you shouldn’t have to suffer for too long.</f_theory></structure>
        
        <structure p="paragraph">That said, pain in your <identity sexuality="cock, balls, pussy,">cock, balls, pussy,</identity> or abdomen can be a sign of something more serious, so if you have 
            these kinds of symptoms at times other than when you have been turned on and not had an <identity sexuality="orgasm">orgasm</identity>, go see your doctor 
            just to be sure.</structure>
        
        <structure p="paragraph">FYI, <identity gender="women">women</identity> <f_theory f_terf="also experience increased blood flow to their genitals when they are turned on and can experience a similar sensation when they don’t have an">also experience increased blood flow to their genitals when they are turned on and can experience a 
                similar sensation when they don’t have an</f_theory> <identity sexuality="orgasm">orgasm.</identity> Let’s call that <f_theory f_rad_fem="purple pussy!">purple pussy!</f_theory></structure>
    </main>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
</document>
