<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- There are still some anxieties about copyright, so the "Punk Planet" files will be a temporary placeholder !--> 
<?xml-model href="../digmethodsfem_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<document> 
    <meta>
<title>Excerpt from Punk Planet 52 </title>
<author>Jenny Tatone</author>
<publication_date>2002 Nov-Dec</publication_date>
   </meta>  
    <main>

<structure>You’ve been in the band and been a musician for a long time. Has it been something that you’ve always known you wanted to do?</structure>

        <structure>No. I wasn’t musical at all growing up. I tried to take a piano lesson here and there and tried to take choir in elementary school on occasion but I never felt I had much talent for any of it, although I’ve always loved music. But I never really thought I had a talent for it—or even the courage to do it myself. \ I was actually already out of college and in a corporate job when I realized that it wasn’t for me. I wasn’t satisfied or fulfilled and I realized just how much I love music. I got this urge and inspiration to do it myself and picked up a guitar and moved to New York with basically no knowledge of anything. I put an ad in the Village Voice looking for peo¬ ple to do it with for fun. I had no idea it would take off and become what it’s become. I have to pinch myself every day and be like, "Am I really doing this? Wow, I’m good at writing songs.” We have a cool thing going on and I’m grateful for it and thrilled that I took the plunge and just did it. I never would have known.</structure>

<structure>I wanted to talk about your overall sound. The album is a really nice mixture of the darker side but also has catchy pop parts too. What brought you to that mix?</structure>

        <structure>I don’t think it’s anything conscious that I know of necessarily ’cause I was exposed to so many different types of music growing

up. But I’ve always had an affinity for melodies and harmonies. Growing up, I would be into the Beach Boys or old ’60s girl group harmonies. But I also really liked Kiss, The Who, and things that really rocked. All that stuff just kind of seeps in unconsciously and it’s been reflected back out with the music.</structure>

        <structure>Do you write all the music as well?</structure>

        <structure>I’ve written the majority of the music since the band has been around, but everyone who’s been in the band has been really musical and writes and contributes a lot. It’s a situation where everyone is encouraged to contribute, but it just hap¬ pens to be that I’m the most prolific. I guess I’m kind of the voice of the band in a sense—the steady foundation. But there’s been contributions along the way here and there and there will be on the new album as well from other people in the band, which I really like.</structure>

        <structure>Do other people in the band bring different influences that are distinct form yours, or are you all pretty similar?

            <structure>I think each person brings their own thing but we always seem to be able to incorpo¬ rate it into our sound, make it cohesive and make it a Hissyfits song even if it’s coming from a different place. For instance, my new viola player, Karen, obviously had a lot of classical training and definitely brings a lot of new and different ideas in and I think everyone will get to see that on the new album. But I think people are in a band together because they do have at least some similar sensibility or something similar that they like in music. Otherwise they probably wouldn’t have gotten the band together in the first place. Honestly, if I did all the writing, it would be boring. I need different input sometimes. And I do tend to have a very poppy sensibility and sometimes what the other people are bringing in helps to counter that with a cool bass line or a cool drum beat. I feel very fortunate that everyone I’ve ever worked with, we haven’t always been exactly the same, but we’ve always complimented each other really well to make something cool together.
</main>
</document>
