<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- There are still some anxieties about copyright, so the "Punk Planet" files will be a temporary placeholder !--> 

<?xml-model href="../digmethodsfem_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<document>
    <meta>
        <title>DIY SEX: EARLY TO BED</title>
        <author>Sex Lady Searah</author>
        <publication_date>2004 July-Aug</publication_date>
      
    </meta>
    <main>
        Ah, blue balls. As a girl, I grew up thinking that <power_system p_patriarchy="blue balls">blue balls</power_system> were <power_system p_patriarchy="nothing more than a sad excuse for guys to pressure girls into having sex">nothing more than a sad excuse for guys to pressure girls into having sex</power_system>— ’’Gome on baby, you got me all turned on, now you have to fuck me or I’ll get blue balls. ” I figured it was just some made-up term for sexual frustration. Then I became a dyke and I never thought about them again until I got this letter. So I did a little research and, with some help from the good people of scarleteen.com, I now know that it is indeed a real condition, albeit not a very serious one.
        
        The technical term for blue balls is vasocongestion and it works like this: When a man becomes aroused, the arteries carrying blood to the genital area enlarge, while the veins carrying blood away from the genital area become more constricted than they are when you aren’t turned on. This causes an increase in the amount of blood trapped in the penis and testicles, which in turn helps you to get your nice, stiff erection and swollen balls. When you have an orgasm, the arteries and veins return to their normal size. If you don’t have an orgasm, that blood can get trapped in there and can lead to an achy, sometimes painful feeling in the testicles. The term "blue balls” comes from the bluish tint that nuts can take on when they are engorged. This pain, however, can usually be easily eradicated by masturbating (when’s the last time someone prescribed that for pain?) or, some say, by taking a cold shower or exercising. Obviously, this condition is never an excuse to try and talk anyone into touchingyour dick if they don 't want to. You are at absolutely no risk for any damage to your cock and, from what I gather, most guys can easily make themselves come in a matter of minutes, so you shouldn’t have to suffer for too long.
        
        That said, pain in your cock, balls, pussy, or abdomen can be a sign of something more serious, so if you have these kinds of symptoms at times other than when you have been turned on and not had an orgasm, go see your doctor just to be sure.
        
        FYI, women also experience increased blood flow to their genitals when they are turned on and can experience a similar sensation when they don’t have an orgasm. Let’s call that purple pussy!
    </main>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
</document>
