<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Polly, feminist magazine relating the greek myth of the furies to current feminist issues -->
<document> 
    <meta>
        <title>The Furies: Lesbian/Feminist Monthly (v. 1)</title>
        <author>Ginny Berson</author>
        <publication_date>January 1972</publication_date>
    </meta>
    <main>
        <p>
            The story of the Furies is the story of strong, powerful women, the "Angry Ones", the
            avengers of matricide, the protectors of women. Three Greek Goddesses, they were described (by
            men) as having snakes for hair, blood-shot eyes, and bats' wings; like Lesbians today, they were
            cursed and feared. They were born when Heaven (the male symbol) was castrated by his son at the
            urging of Earth (the female symbol). The blood from the wound fell on Earth and fertilized her,
            and the Furies were born. Their names were Alecto (Never-ceasing), Tisiphone (Avenger of Blood),
            and Magaera (Grudger). Once extremely powerful, they represented the supremacy of women and the
            primacy of mother right. 
        </p>
        <p>
            Their most famous exploit (famous because in it they lost much of their
            power) involved Orestes in the last episode connected with the cycle of the Trojan War. Orestes,
            acting on the orders of the Sun God Apollo, killed his mother Clytemnestra, because she had
            killed his father. Clytemnestra had killed the father because he had sacrificed their daughter
            Iphigenia, in order to get favorable winds so his fleet could sail to Troy. The Furies tormented
            Orestes: they literally drove him crazy, putting him under a spell where for days he could not
            eat or wash his bloodstained hands. He bit off his finger to try to appease them, but to no
            avail. Finally, in desperation, Orestes went before the court of Athena to plead his case. 
        </p>
        <p>
            The point at issue was whether matricide was justifiable to avenge your father's murder, or in other
            words, whether men or women were to dominate. Apollo defended Orestes and totally denied the
            importance of motherhood, claiming that women were no more than passive sperm receptacles for
            men, and that the father was the only parent worthy of the name. One might have thought that
            Athena, Goddess of Wisdom, would have condemned Orestes, but Athena was the creation of the male
            God, Zeus, sprung full-grown from his head, the first token woman. Athena decided for Orestes.
            Some mythologists say that Zeus, Athena, and Apollo had conspired from the beginning, ordering
            Orestes to kill his mother in order to put an end, once and for all, to the religious belief
            that motherhood was more divine than fatherhood. In any case, that was the result. 
        </p>
        <p>
            The Furies were, of course, furious, and threatened to lay waste the city of Athens. But Athena had a
            direct line to Zeus, King of the Gods; she told the Furies to accept the new male supremacist
            order or lose everything. Some of the Furies and their followers relented, the fest pursued
            Orestes until his death. 
        </p>
        <p>
            We call our paper The FURIES because we are also angry. We are angry
            because we are oppressed by male supremacy. We have been fucked over all our lives by a system
            which is based on the domination of men over women, which defines male as good and female as
            only as good as the man you are with. It is a system in which heterosexuality is rigidly
            enforced and Lesbianism rigidly suppressed. It is a system which has further divided us by
            class, race, and nationality. 
        </p>
        <p>
            We are working to change this system which has kept us separate and powerless for so long. We are a collective of twelve Lesbians living and working in
            Washington, D.C. We are rural and urban; from the Southwest, Midwest, South and Northeast. Our
            ages range from 18 to 28. We are high school dropORESTES PURSUED BY FURIE S outs and Ph.D.
            candidates. We are lower class, middle and upper-middle class. We are white. Some of us have
            been Lesbians for twelve years, others for ten months. We are committed to ending all
            oppressions by attacking their roots--male supremacy.
        </p>
        <p>
            We believe The FURIES will make important contributions to the growing movement to destroy sexism. As a collective, in addition to outside
            projects, we are spending much time building an ideology which is the basis for action. For too
            long, women in the Movement have fallen prey to the very male propaganda they seek to refute.
            They have rejected thought, building an ideology, and all intellectual activity as the realm of
            m^n, and tried to build a politics based only on feelings--the area traditionally left to women.
            The philosophy has been, "if it feels good, it's O.K. If not, forget it." But that is like
            saying that strength. which is a "male" characteristic, should-b"e left to men, and women should
            embrace weakness. Most straight women, to say nothing of men, feel afraid or contemptuous of
            Lesbians. That fear and contempt is similar to the feelings middle class whites have towards
            Blacks or lower class people. These feelings are the result of our socialization and are hardly
            worth glorifying. This is not to say that feelings are irrelevant, only that they are derived
            from our experience which is limited by our class, race, etc. Furthermore, feelings are too
            often used to excuse inaction and inability to change. 
        </p>
        <p>
            A political movement cannot advance without systematic thought and practical organization. The haphazard, non-strategic, zig-zag
            tactics of the straight women's move ment, the male left, and many other so-called revolutionary
            groups have led only to frustration and dissolution. We do not want to make those same mistakes;
            our ideology forms the basis for developing long-range strategies and short-term tactics,
            projects, and actions. 
        </p>
        <p>
            The base of our ideological thought is: Sexism is the root of all other
            oppressions, and Lesbian and woman oppression will not end by smashing capitalism, racism, and
            imperialism. Lesbianism is not a matter of sexual preference, but rather one of political choice
            which every woman must make if she is to become woman-identified and thereby end male supremacy.
            Lesbians, as outcasts from every culture but their own have the most to gain by ending race,
            class, and national supremacy within their own ranks. Lesbians must get out of the straight
            women's movement and form their own movement in order to be taken seriously, to stop straight
            women from oppressing us, and to force straight women to deal with their own Lesbianism.
            Lesbians cannot develop a common politics with women who do not accept Lesbianism as a political
            issue. 
        </p>
        <p>
            In this (see page 8) and following issues of The FURIES we will share our thoughts with
            you. We welcome your comments, letters, articles, fiction, poetry, news, graphics, and support.
            We want to build a movement in this country and in the world which can effectively stop the
            violent, sick, oppressive acts of male supremacy. We want to build a movement which makes all
            people free. 
        </p>
        <p>
            For the Chinese women whose feet were bound and crippled; for the.Ibibos of Africa
            whose clitori were mutilated; for every woman who has ever been raped, physically, economically,
            psychologically, we take the name of the FURIES, Goddesses of Vengeance and protectors of women.
            Ginny Berson.
        </p>
    </main>
</document>
