<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Polly, feminist magazine relating the greek myth of the furies to current feminist issues -->
<?xml-model href="../digmethodsfem_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<document>
    <meta>
        <title>The Furies: Lesbian/Feminist Monthly (v. 1)</title>
        <author>Ginny Berson</author>
        <publication_date>January 1972</publication_date>
    </meta>
    <main>
        <structure p="paragraph">
            <religion r_greekmyth="the furies">The story of the Furies is the story of strong,
                powerful <!--<identity gender="woman">women,</identity> the "Angry Ones", the avengers
                of matricide, the protectors of <identity gender="woman">women</identity>. Three
                Greek Goddesses, they were described (by men) as having snakes for hair, blood-shot
                eyes, and bats' wings; like <identity sexuality="lesbian">Lesbians</identity> today,
                they were cursed and feared. <power_system p_matriarchy="matriarchy">They were born
                    when Heaven <identity gender="man">(the male symbol)</identity> was castrated by
                    his son at the urging of Earth <identity gender="woman">(the female
                        symbol)</identity>.</power_system> The blood from the wound fell on Earth
                and fertilized her, and the Furies were born. Their names were Alecto
                (Never-ceasing), Tisiphone (Avenger of Blood), and Magaera (Grudger). Once extremely
                powerful, they represented <f_theory f_rad_fem="radfem">the supremacy of
                    women</f_theory>--> and the primacy of mother right. </religion>
        </structure>
        <structure p="paragraph">
            <religion r_greekmyth="the furies">Their most famous exploit (famous because in it they
                lost much of their power) involved Orestes in the last episode connected with the
                cycle of the Trojan War. Orestes, acting on the orders of the Sun God Apollo, killed
                his mother Clytemnestra, because she had killed his father. Clytemnestra had killed
                the father because he had sacrificed their daughter Iphigenia, in order to get
                favorable winds so his fleet could sail to Troy. The Furies tormented Orestes: they
                literally drove him crazy, putting him under a spell where for days he could not eat
                or wash his bloodstained hands. He bit off his finger to try to appease them, but to
                no avail. Finally, in desperation, Orestes went before the court of Athena to plead
                his case.</religion>
        </structure>
        <structure p="paragraph">
            The point at issue was whether matricide was
                justifiable to avenge your father's murder, or in other words, whether <identity
                    gender="man">men</identity> or <identity gender="woman">women</identity> were to
            dominate. <religion r_greekmyth="the furies">Apollo defended Orestes and totally denied the importance of motherhood,
            </religion><f_theory f_antifeminist="antifeminist">claiming that women were no more than passive sperm receptacles for men, and that the father was the only parent worthy
                of the name.</f_theory><religion r_greekmyth="the furies"> One might have thought that Athena, Goddess of Wisdom,
                would have condemned Orestes, but Athena was the creation of the male God, Zeus, sprung full-grown from his head, the
                first token woman. Athena decided for Orestes.
                Some mythologists say that Zeus, Athena, and Apollo had conspired from the
                beginning, ordering Orestes to kill his mother in order to put an end, once and for
                all, to the religious belief that motherhood was more divine than fatherhood. In any
                case, that was the result.</religion>
        </structure>
        <structure p="paragraph">
            <religion r_greekmyth="the furies">The Furies were, of course, furious, and threatened
                to lay waste the city of Athens. But Athena had a direct line to Zeus, King of the
                Gods; </religion><f_theory f_antifeminist="antifeminist">she told the Furies to accept the new
                    male supremacist order or lose everything.</f_theory><religion r_greekmyth="the furies"> Some of the Furies and
                their followers relented, the fest pursued Orestes until his death. </religion>
        </structure>
        <structure p="paragraph"> We call our paper The FURIES because we are also angry. We are
            angry because we are oppressed by male supremacy. <power_system
                p_patriarchy="patriarchy">We have been fucked over all our lives by a system which
                is based on the domination of men over women, which defines male as good and female as only
                as good as the man you are with.</power_system>
            It is a system in which <identity sexuality = "straight">heterosexuality</identity> is rigidly
                enforced and <identity sexuality = "lesbian">Lesbianism</identity> rigidly suppressed. It is a system which has
            further divided us by <power_system p_class="class">class</power_system>, <power_system
                p_race="race">race</power_system>, and nationality. </structure>
        <structure p="paragraph"> We are working to change this system which has kept us separate
            and powerless for so long. We are a collective of twelve <identity sexuality="lesbian"
                >Lesbians</identity> living and working in Washington, D.C. We are rural and urban;
            from the Southwest, Midwest, South and Northeast. Our ages range from 18 to 28. We are
            high school dropouts and Ph.D. candidates. We are <class lower="lower">lower
                class,</class>
            <class middle="middle">middle</class> and <class middle="upper middle">upper-middle
                class.</class>
            <identity race="white">We are white.</identity> Some of us have been <identity
                sexuality="lesbian">Lesbians</identity> for twelve years, others for ten months. We
            are committed to ending all oppressions by attacking their roots--male supremacy. </structure>
        <!--<structure photo_caption = "photo"> ORESTES PURSUED BY FURIES </structure> -->
        <structure p="paragraph"> We believe The FURIES will make important contributions to the
            growing movement to destroy sexism. As a collective, in addition to outside projects, we
            are spending much time building an ideology which is the basis for action. For too long,
                <identity gender="woman">women</identity> in the Movement have fallen prey to the
            very <identity gender="man">male</identity> propaganda they seek to refute. They have
            rejected thought, building an ideology, and all intellectual activity as the realm of
                <identity gender="man">men</identity>, and tried to build a politics based only on
            feelings--the area traditionally left to <identity gender="woman">women</identity>. The
            philosophy has been, "if it feels good, it's O.K. If not, forget it." But that is like
            saying that strength. which is a <identity gender="man">"male"</identity>
            characteristic, should-be left to <identity gender="man">men</identity>, and <identity
                gender="woman">women</identity> should embrace weakness. Most <identity
                sexuality="straight">straight</identity>
            <identity gender="woman">women</identity>, to say nothing of <identity gender="man"
                >men</identity>, feel afraid or contemptuous of <identity sexuality="lesbian"
                >Lesbians</identity>. That fear and contempt is similar to the feelings <class
                middle="middle">middle class</class>
            <identity race="white">whites</identity> have towards <identity race="black"
                >Blacks</identity> or <class lower="lower">lower class people.</class> These
            feelings are the result of our socialization and are hardly worth glorifying. This is
            not to say that feelings are irrelevant, only that they are derived from our experience
            which is limited by our class, race, etc. Furthermore, feelings are too often used to
            excuse inaction and inability to change. </structure>
        <structure p="paragraph"> A political movement cannot advance without systematic thought and
            practical organization. The haphazard, non-strategic, zig-zag tactics of the <identity sexuality = "straight">straight</identity>
            <identity gender="woman">women's</identity> movement, the male left, and many other so-called revolutionary groups have led
            only to frustration and dissolution. We do not want to make those same mistakes; our
            ideology forms the basis for developing long-range strategies and short-term tactics,
            projects, and actions. </structure>
        <structure p="paragraph"> The base of our ideological thought is: Sexism is the root of all
            other oppressions, and <identity sexuality="lesbian">Lesbian</identity> and <identity
                gender="woman">woman</identity> oppression will not end by smashing capitalism,
                <power_system p_race="racism">racism</power_system>, and imperialism.<f_theory f_politicallesbian="political lesbian">Lesbianism is not a matter of sexual
                preference, but rather one of political choice which every woman must make if she is
                to become woman-identified and thereby end male supremacy.</f_theory>
            <identity sexuality="lesbian">Lesbians,</identity> as outcasts from every culture but
            their own have the most to gain by ending <power_system p_race = "race">race</power_system>, <power_system p_class = "class">class</power_system>, and national supremacy within
            their own ranks. <f_theory f_politicallesbian="political lesbian">Lesbians must
                get out of the straight women's movement and form their own movement in order to be
                taken seriously, to stop straight women from oppressing us, and to force straight
                women to deal with their own Lesbianism.</f_theory>
            <f_theory f_politicallesbian="political lesbian">Lesbians cannot develop a common
                politics with women who do not accept Lesbianism as a political issue.</f_theory>
        </structure>
        <structure p="paragraph"> In this (see page 8) and following issues of The FURIES we will
            share our thoughts with you. We welcome your comments, letters, articles, fiction,
            poetry, news, graphics, and support. We want to build a movement in this country and in
            the world which can effectively stop the violent, sick, oppressive acts of <identity gender = "man">male</identity>
            supremacy. We want to build a movement which makes all people free. </structure>
        <structure p="paragraph"> For the Chinese <identity gender = "woman">women</identity> whose feet were bound and crippled; for the.
            Ibibos of Africa whose clitori were mutilated; for every <identity gender = "woman">woman</identity> who has ever been raped,
            physically, <power_system p_class="economic">economically</power_system>, psychologically, we take the name of <religion r_greekmyth = "greek myth">the FURIES, Goddesses of
                Vengeance and protectors of women.</religion> Ginny Berson. </structure>
    </main>
</document>
