<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Polly, short poem about the struggles of women at the time -->
<document>
    <meta>
        <title>There was a young woman who swallowed a lie</title>
        <author>Meredith Tax</author>
        <publication_date>1970s</publication_date>
    </meta>
    <main>
    <structure page="page">
        <structure s="stanza"> THERE WAS A YOUNG <identity gender = "woman">WOMAN</identity> WHO SWALLOWED A LIE, We all know why she
            swallowed that lie, PERHAPS SHE'LL DIE! </structure>
    </structure>
    <structure page="page">
        <structure s="stanza"> THERE WAS A YOUNG <identity gender = "woman">WOMAN</identity> WHO SWALLOWED A RULE, <power_system
                p_patriarchy="patriarchy">"Live to serve others"</power_system>, she learned it in
            school. She swallowed the rule to go with the lie, We all know why she swallowed that
            lie, PERHAPS SHE'LL DIE! </structure>
    </structure>
    <structure page="page">
        <structure s="stanza"> THERE WAS A YOUNG <identity gender = "woman">WOMAN</identity> WHO SWALLOWED SOME FLUFF; <class economic="beauty-industry">Lipstick &amp;
                candy &amp; powder &amp; puff</class> -- She swallowed the FLUFF to sweeten the rule, She
            swallowed the rule to go with the lie, We all know why she swallowed that lie, PERHAPS
            SHE'LL DIE! </structure>
    </structure>
    <structure page="page">
        <structure s="stanza"> THERE WAS A YOUNG <identity gender = "woman">WOMAN</identity> WHO SWALLOWED A LINE, <power_system
                p_patriarchy="patriarchy"> "I like 'em dumb baby, you suit me fine." </power_system>
            She swallowed the line to go with the FLUFF She swallowed the FLUFF to sweeten the rule,
            She swallowed the rule to go with the lie, We all know why she swallowed that lie,
            PERHAPS SHE'LL DIE! </structure>
    </structure>
    <structure page="page">
        <structure s="stanza">
            <power_system p_patriarchy="patriarchy"> THERE WAS A YOUNG <identity gender = "woman">WOMAN</identity> WHO SWALLOWED A PILL,
                Might have said, "No," but she hadn't the will. </power_system> She swallowed the
            pill to go with the line, She swallowed the line to go with the FLUFF She swallowed the
            FLUFF to sweeten the rule, She swallowed the rule to go with the lie, We all know why
            she swallowed that lie, PERHAPS SHE'LL DIE! </structure>
    </structure>
    <structure page="page">
        <structure s="stanza"> THERE WAS A YOUNG <identity gender = "woman">WOMAN</identity> WHO SWALLOWED A RING, <power_system p_patriarchy="patriarchy">Looked like a princess
            but felt like a thing. </power_system> She swallowed the ring to make up for the pill, She swallowed the
            pill to go with the line, She swallowed the line to go with the FLUFF She swallowed the
            FLUFF to sweeten the rule, She swallowed the rule to go with the lie, We all know why
            she swallowed that lie... PERHAPS SHE'LL DIE! </structure>
    </structure>
    <structure page="page">
        <structure s="stanza"> THERE WAS A YOUNG <identity gender = "woman">WOMAN</identity> WHO SWALLOWED SOME SPOCK, <power_system p_patriarchy="patriarchy">"Stay at home,
            Mother, take care of your flock."</power_system> She swalloed the Spock to go with the ring, She
            swallowed the ring to make up for the pill, She swallowed the pill to go with the line,
            She swallowed the line to go with the FLUFF She swallowed the FLUFF to sweeten the rule,
            She swallowed the rule to go with the lie, We all know why she swallowed that lie
            PERHAPS SHE'LL DIE! </structure>
    </structure>
    <structure page="page">
        <structure s="stanza"> ONE DAY THIS YOUNG <identity gender = "woman">WOMAN</identity> WOKE UP &amp; SHE SAID, "I've swallowed so
            much, I wish I were dead. I swallowed it all to go with the Spock, I swallowed the Spock
            to go with the ring, I swallowed the ring to make up for the pill, I swallowed the pill
            to go with the line, I swallowed the line to go with the FLUFF, I swallowed the FLUFF to
            sweeten the rule, I swallowed the rule to go with the lie, Why in the world did I
            swallow that lie!? PERHAPS I'LL DIE!" </structure>
    </structure>
    <structure page="page">
        <structure s="stanza"> <f_theory f_rad_fem = "?">SHE RAN TO HER SISTERS, IT WASN'T TOO LATE TO BE LIBERATED,
            REGURGITATE.</f_theory> She threw up the Spock &amp; threw up the ring, Looked like a princess, but
            felt like a thing; She threw up the pill &amp; threw up the line, "I like 'em dumb,
            baby, you suit me fine; She threw up the FLUFF and threw up the rule, "Live to serve
            others," she learned it in school; <f_theory f_rad_fem = "?">And last but not least, she threw up that lie, - We
            all know why she threw up that lie, SHE WILL NOT DIE!!</f_theory> </structure>
    </structure>
    </main>
</document>
